<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2010 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN"
          "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">


<document>

  <header>
    <title> 
      Bulk Loads in HBase
    </title>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Overview</title>
      <p>
        HBase includes several methods of loading data into tables.
        The most straightforward method is to either use the TableOutputFormat
        class from a MapReduce job, or use the normal client APIs; however,
        these are not always the most efficient methods.
      </p>
      <p>
        This document describes HBase's bulk load functionality. The bulk load
        feature uses a MapReduce job to output table data in HBase's internal
        data format, and then directly loads the data files into a running
        cluster.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Bulk Load Architecture</title>
      <p>
        The HBase bulk load process consists of two main steps.
      </p>
      <subsection>
        <title>Preparing data via a MapReduce job</title>
        <p>
          The first step of a bulk load is to generate HBase data files from
          a MapReduce job using HFileOutputFormat. This output format writes
          out data in HBase's internal storage format so that they can be
          later loaded very efficiently into the cluster.
        </p>
        <p>
          In order to function efficiently, HFileOutputFormat must be configured
          such that each output HFile fits within a single region. In order to
          do this, jobs use Hadoop's TotalOrderPartitioner class to partition the
          map output into disjoint ranges of the key space, corresponding to the
          key ranges of the regions in the table.
        </p>
        <p>
          HFileOutputFormat includes a convenience function, <code>configureIncrementalLoad()</code>,
          which automatically sets up a TotalOrderPartitioner based on the current
          region boundaries of a table.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection>
        <title>Completing the data load</title>
        <p>
          After the data has been prepared using <code>HFileOutputFormat</code>, it
          is loaded into the cluster using a command line tool. This command line tool
          iterates through the prepared data files, and for each one determines the
          region the file belongs to. It then contacts the appropriate Region Server
          which adopts the HFile, moving it into its storage directory and making
          the data available to clients.
        </p>
        <p>
          If the region boundaries have changed during the course of bulk load
          preparation, or between the preparation and completion steps, the bulk
          load commandline utility will automatically split the data files into
          pieces corresponding to the new boundaries. This process is not
          optimally efficient, so users should take care to minimize the delay between
          preparing a bulk load and importing it into the cluster, especially
          if other clients are simultaneously loading data through other means.
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Preparing a bulk load using the <code>importtsv</code> tool</title>
      <p>
        HBase ships with a command line tool called <code>importtsv</code>. This tool
        is available by running <code>hadoop jar /path/to/hbase-VERSION.jar importtsv</code>.
        Running this tool with no arguments prints brief usage information:
      </p>
      <code><pre>
Usage: importtsv -Dimporttsv.columns=a,b,c &lt;tablename&gt; &lt;inputdir&gt;

Imports the given input directory of TSV data into the specified table.

The column names of the TSV data must be specified using the -Dimporttsv.columns
option. This option takes the form of comma-separated column names, where each
column name is either a simple column family, or a columnfamily:qualifier. The special
column name HBASE_ROW_KEY is used to designate that this column should be used
as the row key for each imported record. You must specify exactly one column
to be the row key.

In order to prepare data for a bulk data load, pass the option:
  -Dimporttsv.bulk.output=/path/for/output

Other options that may be specified with -D include:
  -Dimporttsv.skip.bad.lines=false - fail if encountering an invalid line
</pre></code>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Importing the prepared data using the <code>completebulkload</code> tool</title>
      <p>
        After a data import has been prepared using the <code>importtsv</code> tool, the
        <code>completebulkload</code> tool is used to import the data into the running cluster.
      </p>
      <p>
        The <code>completebulkload</code> tool simply takes the same output path where
        <code>importtsv</code> put its results, and the table name. For example:
      </p>
      <code>$ hadoop jar hbase-VERSION.jar completebulkload /user/todd/myoutput mytable</code>
      <p>
        This tool will run quickly, after which point the new data will be visible in
        the cluster.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Advanced Usage</title>
      <p>
        Although the <code>importtsv</code> tool is useful in many cases, advanced users may
        want to generate data programatically, or import data from other formats. To get
        started doing so, dig into <code>ImportTsv.java</code> and check the JavaDoc for
        HFileOutputFormat.
      </p>
      <p>
        The import step of the bulk load can also be done programatically. See the
        <code>LoadIncrementalHFiles</code> class for more information.
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>