<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" 
          "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document> 

  <header> 
    <title>Welcome to Hadoop!</title> 
  </header> 

  <body>
    <p>
    Hadoop is a software platform lets one easily write and run
    applications that process vast amounts of data.</p>

    <p>Here's what makes Hadoop especially useful:</p>
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Scalable:</strong>
      Hadoop can reliably store and process petabytes.</li>
      <li><strong>Economical:</strong>
      It distributes the data and processing across clusters of
      commonly available computers. These clusters can number into the
      thousands of nodes.</li>
      <li><strong>Efficient:</strong>
      By distributing the data, Hadoop can process it in parallel on
      the nodes where the data is located. This makes it extremely
      rapid.</li>
      <li><strong>Reliable:</strong>
      Hadoop automatically maintains multiple copies of data and
      automatically redeploys computing tasks based on failures.</li>
    </ul>
    <p>
    Hadoop implements <a
    href="http://wiki.apache.org/lucene-hadoop/HadoopMapReduce">MapReduce</a>,
    using the Hadoop Distributed File System (<a
    href="hdfs_design.html"><acronym title="Hadoop Distributed File
    System">HDFS</acronym></a>) (see figure below.)  MapReduce divides
    applications into many small blocks of work.  HDFS creates
    multiple replicas of data blocks for reliability, placing them on
    compute nodes around the cluster.  MapReduce can then process the
    data where it is located.
    </p>

    <figure alt="architecture" src="images/architecture.gif" />

    <section>
      <title> Getting Started </title>
      <p>
      The Hadoop project plans to scale Hadoop up to handling thousands of computers. However, to begin with you can start by installing in on a single machine or a very small cluster.
      </p>
      <ol>
        <li><a href="documentation.html">Learn about</a> Hadoop by reading the documentation.</li>
        <li><a href="releases.html">Download</a> Hadoop from the release page.</li>
        <li><a href="ext:overview">Install and configure</a> Hadoop. Scroll down the page.</li>
        <li><a href="mailing_lists.html">Discuss it</a> on the mailing list.</li>
      </ol>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title> Getting Involved </title>
      <p>
      Hadoop is an open source volunteer project under the Apache Software Foundation. We encourage you to learn about the project and contribute your expertise. Here are some starter links:
      </p>
      <ol>
        <li>See our <a href="http://wiki.apache.org/lucene-hadoop/HowToContribute">How to Contribute to Hadoop</a> page.</li>
        <li>Give us <a href="issue_tracking.html">feedback</a>: What can we do better?</li>
        <li>Join the <a href="mailing_lists.html">mailing list</a>: Meet the community.</li>
      </ol>
    </section>

  </body>

</document>
