<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" 
          "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">

<document> 

  <header> 
    <title>Releases</title> 
  </header> 

  <body> 

    <section>
      <title>Download</title>

      <p>Releases may be downloaded from Apache mirrors.</p>

      <p>
      <a href="http://www.apache.org/dyn/closer.cgi/lucene/hadoop/">
      <strong><strong>Download a release now!</strong></strong></a>
      </p>

      <p>On the mirror, all recent releases are available, but are not
      guaranteed to be stable. For stable releases, look in the stable
      directory.
      </p>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Release Notes</title>

      <p>Release notes for Hadoop releases are available in Jira.</p>

      <p>
      <a href="http://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HADOOP?report=com.atlassian.jira.plugin.system.project:changelog-panel">
      <strong><strong>Browse release notes now!</strong></strong></a>
      </p>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>News</title>

      <section>
      <title>25 July, 2007: release 0.13.1 available</title>
      <p>This fixes critical bugs in the 0.13.0 release.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title> 8 June, 2007: release 0.13.0 available </title>
        <p>
        In addition to new features, this release contains significant performance and reliability improvements.
        For example, MapReduce sort performance on large clusters has <a href="http://wiki.apache.org/lucene-hadoop-data/attachments/FAQ/attachments/sort900-20070607.png">doubled</a>.
        </p>
        <note>
        When upgrading an existing <acronym title="Hadoop Distributed File System">HDFS</acronym> filesystem to this release, you should first start HDFS with <code>bin/start-dfs.sh -upgrade</code>
        which makes it possible to revert the upgrade. For more information on this issue, see <a href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HADOOP-702#action_12482953">HADOOP-702</a>. 
        </note>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title> 8 June, 2006: <acronym title="Frequently Asked Questions">FAQ</acronym> added to Wiki </title>
        <p>
        Hadoop now has a <a href="http://wiki.apache.org/lucene-hadoop/FAQ">FAQ</a>. Please help make this more complete!
        </p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title> 5 May, 2006: release 0.2.0 available </title>
        <p>
        We are now aiming for monthly releases. There have been many bug fixes and improvements in the past month.
        MapReduce and DFS are now fairly reliable on clusters with up to 200 nodes.
        </p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title> 6 February, 2006: nightly builds </title>
        <p>
        Hadoop now has nightly builds. This automatically creates a <a href="http://lucene.zones.apache.org:8080/hudson/job/Hadoop-Nightly/">downloadable version of Hadoop every night</a>.
        All unit tests must pass, or a message is sent to the developers mailing list and no new version is created.
        This also updates the <a href="http://lucene.apache.org/hadoop/api/index.html">javadoc</a>.
        </p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title> 3 February, 2006: Hadoop code moved out of Nutch </title>
        <p>
        The Hadoop code has now been moved into its own Subversion tree, renamed into packages under org.apache.hadoop.
        All unit tests pass, but little else has yet been tested.
        </p>
      </section>
     
    </section>

  </body>

</document>
