<?xml version="1.0"?>
  <chapter xml:id="configuration"
      version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
      xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Configuration</title>
    <para>
        HBase uses the same configuration system as Hadoop.
        To configure a deploy, edit a file of environment variables
        in <filename>conf/hbase-env.sh</filename> -- this configuration
        is used mostly by the launcher shell scripts getting the cluster
        off the ground -- and then add configuration to an XML file to
        do things like override HBase defaults, tell HBase what Filesystem to
        use, and the location of the ZooKeeper ensemble
        <footnote>
<para>
Be careful editing XML.  Make sure you close all elements.
Run your file through <command>xmllint</command> or similar
to ensure well-formedness of your document after an edit session.
</para>
        </footnote>
        .
    </para>

    <para>When running in distributed mode, after you make
    an edit to an HBase configuration, make sure you copy the
    content of the <filename>conf</filename> directory to
    all nodes of the cluster.  HBase will not do this for you.
    Use <command>rsync</command>.</para>


    <section xml:id="hbase.site">
    <title><filename>hbase-site.xml</filename> and <filename>hbase-default.xml</filename></title>
    <para>Just as in Hadoop where you add site-specific HDFS configuration
    to the <filename>hdfs-site.xml</filename> file,
    for HBase, site specific customizations go into
    the file <filename>conf/hbase-site.xml</filename>.
    For the list of configurable properties, see
    <xref linkend="hbase_default_configurations" />
    below or view the raw <filename>hbase-default.xml</filename>
    source file in the HBase source code at
    <filename>src/main/resources</filename>.
    </para>
    <para>
    Not all configuration options make it out to
    <filename>hbase-default.xml</filename>.  Configuration
    that it is thought rare anyone would change can exist only
    in code; the only way to turn up such configurations is
    via a reading of the source code itself.
    </para>
      <para>
      Currently, changes here will require a cluster restart for HBase to notice the change.
      </para>
    <!--The file hbase-default.xml is generated as part of
    the build of the hbase site.  See the hbase pom.xml.
    The generated file is a docbook section with a glossary
    in it-->
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      href="../../target/site/hbase-default.xml" />
    </section>

      <section xml:id="hbase.env.sh">
      <title><filename>hbase-env.sh</filename></title>
      <para>Set HBase environment variables in this file.
      Examples include options to pass the JVM on start of
      an HBase daemon such as heap size and garbarge collector configs.
      You can also set configurations for HBase configuration, log directories,
      niceness, ssh options, where to locate process pid files,
      etc. Open the file at
      <filename>conf/hbase-env.sh</filename> and peruse its content.
      Each option is fairly well documented.  Add your own environment
      variables here if you want them read by HBase daemons on startup.</para>
      <para>
      Changes here will require a cluster restart for HBase to notice the change.
      </para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="log4j">
      <title><filename>log4j.properties</filename></title>
      <para>Edit this file to change rate at which HBase files
      are rolled and to change the level at which HBase logs messages.
      </para>
      <para>
      Changes here will require a cluster restart for HBase to notice the change
      though log levels can be changed for particular daemons via the HBase UI.
      </para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="important_configurations">
      <title>The Important Configurations</title>
      <para>Below we list what the <emphasis>important</emphasis>
      Configurations.  We've divided this section into
      required configuration and worth-a-look recommended configs.
      </para>


      <section xml:id="required_configuration"><title>Required Configurations</title>
          <para>See <xref linkend="requirements" />.
      It lists at least two required configurations needed running HBase bearing
      load: i.e. <xref linkend="ulimit" /> and
      <xref linkend="dfs.datanode.max.xcievers" />.
      </para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="recommended_configurations"><title>Recommended Configuations</title>
          <section xml:id="zookeeper.session.timeout"><title><varname>zookeeper.session.timeout</varname></title>
          <para>The default timeout is three minutes (specified in milliseconds). This means
              that if a server crashes, it will be three minutes before the Master notices
              the crash and starts recovery. You might like to tune the timeout down to
              a minute or even less so the Master notices failures the sooner.
              Before changing this value, be sure you have your JVM garbage collection
              configuration under control otherwise, a long garbage collection that lasts
              beyond the ZooKeeper session timeout will take out
              your RegionServer (You might be fine with this -- you probably want recovery to start
          on the server if a RegionServer has been in GC for a long period of time).</para> 

      <para>To change this configuration, edit <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>,
          copy the changed file around the cluster and restart.</para>

          <para>We set this value high to save our having to field noob questions up on the mailing lists asking
              why a RegionServer went down during a massive import.  The usual cause is that their JVM is untuned and
              they are running into long GC pauses.  Our thinking is that
              while users are  getting familiar with HBase, we'd save them having to know all of its
              intricacies.  Later when they've built some confidence, then they can play
              with configuration such as this.
          </para>
      </section>
          <section xml:id="zookeeper.instances"><title>Number of ZooKeeper Instances</title>
          <para>It is best to use an odd number of machines (1, 3, 5) for a ZooKeeper ensemble.
          See the <link xlink:href="http://wiki.apache.org/hadoop/ZooKeeper/FAQ#A7">ZooKeeper Wiki</link> or the 
          <link xlink:href="http://zookeeper.apache.org/doc/r3.3.3/zookeeperAdmin.html#sc_zkMulitServerSetup">ZooKeeper documentation</link> 
          for more information on ZooKeeper sizing.
          </para>
      </section>
          <section xml:id="hbase.regionserver.handler.count"><title><varname>hbase.regionserver.handler.count</varname></title>
          <para>
          This setting defines the number of threads that are kept open to answer
          incoming requests to user tables. The default of 10 is rather low in order to
          prevent users from killing their region servers when using large write buffers
          with a high number of concurrent clients. The rule of thumb is to keep this
          number low when the payload per request approaches the MB (big puts, scans using
          a large cache) and high when the payload is small (gets, small puts, ICVs, deletes).
          </para>
          <para>
          It is safe to set that number to the
          maximum number of incoming clients if their payload is small, the typical example
          being a cluster that serves a website since puts aren't typically buffered
          and most of the operations are gets.
          </para>
          <para>
          The reason why it is dangerous to keep this setting high is that the aggregate
          size of all the puts that are currently happening in a region server may impose
          too much pressure on its memory, or even trigger an OutOfMemoryError. A region server
          running on low memory will trigger its JVM's garbage collector to run more frequently
          up to a point where GC pauses become noticeable (the reason being that all the memory
          used to keep all the requests' payloads cannot be trashed, no matter how hard the
          garbage collector tries). After some time, the overall cluster
          throughput is affected since every request that hits that region server will take longer,
          which exacerbates the problem even more.
          </para>
          </section>
      <section xml:id="big_memory">
        <title>Configuration for large memory machines</title>
        <para>
          HBase ships with a reasonable, conservative configuration that will
          work on nearly all
          machine types that people might want to test with. If you have larger
          machines -- HBase has 8G and larger heap -- you might the following configuration options helpful.
          TODO.
        </para>

      </section>

      <section xml:id="lzo">
      <title>LZO compression<indexterm><primary>LZO</primary></indexterm></title>
      <para>You should consider enabling LZO compression.  Its
      near-frictionless and in most all cases boosts performance.
      </para>
      <para>Unfortunately, HBase cannot ship with LZO because of
      the licensing issues; HBase is Apache-licensed, LZO is GPL.
      Therefore LZO install is to be done post-HBase install.
      See the <link xlink:href="http://wiki.apache.org/hadoop/UsingLzoCompression">Using LZO Compression</link>
      wiki page for how to make LZO work with HBase.
      </para>
      <para>A common problem users run into when using LZO is that while initial
      setup of the cluster runs smooth, a month goes by and some sysadmin goes to
      add a machine to the cluster only they'll have forgotten to do the LZO
      fixup on the new machine.  In versions since HBase 0.90.0, we should
      fail in a way that makes it plain what the problem is, but maybe not.
      Remember you read this paragraph<footnote><para>See
              <xref linkend="hbase.regionserver.codecs" />
      for a feature to help protect against failed LZO install</para></footnote>.
      </para>
      <para>See also <xref linkend="compression" />
      at the tail of this book.</para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="bigger.regions">
      <title>Bigger Regions</title>
      <para>
      Consider going to larger regions to cut down on the total number of regions
      on your cluster. Generally less Regions to manage makes for a smoother running
      cluster (You can always later manually split the big Regions should one prove
      hot and you want to spread the request load over the cluster).  By default,
      regions are 256MB in size.  You could run with
      1G.  Some run with even larger regions; 4G or even larger.  Adjust
      <code>hbase.hregion.max.filesize</code> in your <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>.
      </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="disable.splitting">
      <title>Managed Splitting</title>
      <para>
      Rather than let HBase auto-split your Regions, manage the splitting manually
      <footnote><para>What follows is taken from the javadoc at the head of
      the <classname>org.apache.hadoop.hbase.util.RegionSplitter</classname> tool
      added to HBase post-0.90.0 release.
      </para>
      </footnote>.
 With growing amounts of data, splits will continually be needed. Since
 you always know exactly what regions you have, long-term debugging and
 profiling is much easier with manual splits. It is hard to trace the logs to
 understand region level problems if it keeps splitting and getting renamed.
 Data offlining bugs + unknown number of split regions == oh crap! If an
 <classname>HLog</classname> or <classname>StoreFile</classname>
 was mistakenly unprocessed by HBase due to a weird bug and
 you notice it a day or so later, you can be assured that the regions
 specified in these files are the same as the current regions and you have
 less headaches trying to restore/replay your data.
 You can finely tune your compaction algorithm. With roughly uniform data
 growth, it's easy to cause split / compaction storms as the regions all
 roughly hit the same data size at the same time. With manual splits, you can
 let staggered, time-based major compactions spread out your network IO load.
      </para>
      <para>
 How do I turn off automatic splitting? Automatic splitting is determined by the configuration value
 <code>hbase.hregion.max.filesize</code>. It is not recommended that you set this
 to <varname>Long.MAX_VALUE</varname> in case you forget about manual splits. A suggested setting
 is 100GB, which would result in > 1hr major compactions if reached.
 </para>
 <para>What's the optimal number of pre-split regions to create?
 Mileage will vary depending upon your application.
 You could start low with 10 pre-split regions / server and watch as data grows
 over time. It's better to err on the side of too little regions and rolling split later.
 A more complicated answer is that this depends upon the largest storefile
 in your region. With a growing data size, this will get larger over time. You
 want the largest region to be just big enough that the <classname>Store</classname> compact
 selection algorithm only compacts it due to a timed major. If you don't, your
 cluster can be prone to compaction storms as the algorithm decides to run
 major compactions on a large series of regions all at once. Note that
 compaction storms are due to the uniform data growth, not the manual split
 decision.
 </para>
<para> If you pre-split your regions too thin, you can increase the major compaction
interval by configuring <varname>HConstants.MAJOR_COMPACTION_PERIOD</varname>. If your data size
grows too large, use the (post-0.90.0 HBase) <classname>org.apache.hadoop.hbase.util.RegionSplitter</classname>
script to perform a network IO safe rolling split
of all regions.
</para>
      </section>

      </section>

      </section>
      <section xml:id="client_dependencies"><title>Client configuration and dependencies connecting to an HBase cluster</title>

      <para>
          Since the HBase Master may move around, clients bootstrap by looking to ZooKeeper for
          current critical locations.  ZooKeeper is where all these values are kept.  Thus clients
          require the location of the ZooKeeper ensemble information before they can do anything else.
          Usually this the ensemble location is kept out in the <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename> and
          is picked up by the client from the <varname>CLASSPATH</varname>.</para>

        <para>If you are configuring an IDE to run a HBase client, you should
            include the <filename>conf/</filename> directory on your classpath so
            <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename> settings can be found (or
            add <filename>src/test/resources</filename> to pick up the hbase-site.xml
            used by tests).
      </para>
      <para>
          Minimally, a client of HBase needs the hbase, hadoop, log4j, commons-logging, commons-lang,
          and ZooKeeper jars in its <varname>CLASSPATH</varname> connecting to a cluster.
      </para>
        <para>
          An example basic <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename> for client only
          might look as follows:
          <programlisting><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="configuration.xsl"?>
<configuration>
  <property>
    <name>hbase.zookeeper.quorum</name>
    <value>example1,example2,example3</value>
    <description>The directory shared by region servers.
    </description>
  </property>
</configuration>
]]></programlisting>
        </para>
        <section>
        <title>Java client configuration</title>
        <subtitle>How Java reads <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename> content</subtitle>
        <para>The configuration used by a java client is kept
        in an <link xlink:href="http://hbase.apache.org/apidocs/org/apache/hadoop/hbase/HBaseConfiguration">HBaseConfiguration</link> instance.
        The factory method on HBaseConfiguration, <code>HBaseConfiguration.create();</code>,
        on invocation, will read in the content of the first <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename> found on
        the client's <varname>CLASSPATH</varname>, if one is present
        (Invocation will also factor in any <filename>hbase-default.xml</filename> found;
        an hbase-default.xml ships inside the <filename>hbase.X.X.X.jar</filename>). 
        It is also possible to specify configuration directly without having to read from a
        <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>.  For example, to set the ZooKeeper
        ensemble for the cluster programmatically do as follows:
        <programlisting>Configuration config = HBaseConfiguration.create();
config.set("hbase.zookeeper.quorum", "localhost");  // Here we are running zookeeper locally</programlisting>    
        If multiple ZooKeeper instances make up your ZooKeeper ensemble,
        they may be specified in a comma-separated list (just as in the <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename> file).
        This populated <classname>Configuration</classname> instance can then be passed to an 
        <link xlink:href="http://hbase.apache.org/apidocs/org/apache/hadoop/hbase/client/HTable.html">HTable</link>,
        and so on.
        </para>
        </section>
    </section>

  </chapter>
