<?xml version="1.0"?>
  <chapter xml:id="configuration"
      version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
      xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Configuration</title>
    <para>This chapter is the Not-So-Quick start guide to HBase configuration.</para>
    <para>Please read this chapter carefully and ensure that all requirements have 
      been satisfied.  Failure to do so will cause you (and us) grief debugging strange errors
      and/or data loss.</para>
    
    <para>
        HBase uses the same configuration system as Hadoop.
        To configure a deploy, edit a file of environment variables
        in <filename>conf/hbase-env.sh</filename> -- this configuration
        is used mostly by the launcher shell scripts getting the cluster
        off the ground -- and then add configuration to an XML file to
        do things like override HBase defaults, tell HBase what Filesystem to
        use, and the location of the ZooKeeper ensemble
        <footnote>
<para>
Be careful editing XML.  Make sure you close all elements.
Run your file through <command>xmllint</command> or similar
to ensure well-formedness of your document after an edit session.
</para>
        </footnote>
        .
    </para>

    <para>When running in distributed mode, after you make
    an edit to an HBase configuration, make sure you copy the
    content of the <filename>conf</filename> directory to
    all nodes of the cluster.  HBase will not do this for you.
    Use <command>rsync</command>.</para>
    
    <section xml:id="java">
        <title>Java</title>

        <para>Just like Hadoop, HBase requires java 6 from <link
        xlink:href="http://www.java.com/download/">Oracle</link>. Usually
        you'll want to use the latest version available except the problematic
        u18 (u24 is the latest version as of this writing).</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="os">
        <title>Operating System</title>        
      <section xml:id="ssh">
        <title>ssh</title>

        <para><command>ssh</command> must be installed and
        <command>sshd</command> must be running to use Hadoop's scripts to
        manage remote Hadoop and HBase daemons. You must be able to ssh to all
        nodes, including your local node, using passwordless login (Google
        "ssh passwordless login").</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="dns">
        <title>DNS</title>

        <para>HBase uses the local hostname to self-report it's IP address.
        Both forward and reverse DNS resolving should work.</para>

        <para>If your machine has multiple interfaces, HBase will use the
        interface that the primary hostname resolves to.</para>

        <para>If this is insufficient, you can set
        <varname>hbase.regionserver.dns.interface</varname> to indicate the
        primary interface. This only works if your cluster configuration is
        consistent and every host has the same network interface
        configuration.</para>

        <para>Another alternative is setting
        <varname>hbase.regionserver.dns.nameserver</varname> to choose a
        different nameserver than the system wide default.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="ntp">
        <title>NTP</title>

        <para>The clocks on cluster members should be in basic alignments.
        Some skew is tolerable but wild skew could generate odd behaviors. Run
        <link
        xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Network_Time_Protocol">NTP</link>
        on your cluster, or an equivalent.</para>

        <para>If you are having problems querying data, or "weird" cluster
        operations, check system time!</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="ulimit">
        <title>
          <varname>ulimit</varname><indexterm>
            <primary>ulimit</primary>
            </indexterm>
            and
          <varname>nproc</varname><indexterm>
            <primary>nproc</primary>
            </indexterm>
        </title>

        <para>HBase is a database.  It uses a lot of files all at the same time.
        The default ulimit -n -- i.e. user file limit -- of 1024 on most *nix systems
        is insufficient (On mac os x its 256). Any significant amount of loading will
        lead you to <link xlink:href="http://wiki.apache.org/hadoop/Hbase/FAQ#A6">FAQ: Why do I
        see "java.io.IOException...(Too many open files)" in my logs?</link>.
        You may also notice errors such as <programlisting>
      2010-04-06 03:04:37,542 INFO org.apache.hadoop.hdfs.DFSClient: Exception increateBlockOutputStream java.io.EOFException
      2010-04-06 03:04:37,542 INFO org.apache.hadoop.hdfs.DFSClient: Abandoning block blk_-6935524980745310745_1391901
      </programlisting> Do yourself a favor and change the upper bound on the
        number of file descriptors. Set it to north of 10k. See the above
        referenced FAQ for how.  You should also up the hbase users'
        <varname>nproc</varname> setting; under load, a low-nproc
        setting could manifest as <classname>OutOfMemoryError</classname>
        <footnote><para>See Jack Levin's <link xlink:href="">major hdfs issues</link>
                note up on the user list.</para></footnote>
        <footnote><para>The requirement that a database requires upping of system limits
        is not peculiar to HBase.  See for example the section
        <emphasis>Setting Shell Limits for the Oracle User</emphasis> in
        <link xlink:href="http://www.akadia.com/services/ora_linux_install_10g.html">
        Short Guide to install Oracle 10 on Linux</link>.</para></footnote>.
       </para>

        <para>To be clear, upping the file descriptors and nproc for the user who is
        running the HBase process is an operating system configuration, not an
        HBase configuration. Also, a common mistake is that administrators
        will up the file descriptors for a particular user but for whatever
        reason, HBase will be running as some one else. HBase prints in its
        logs as the first line the ulimit its seeing. Ensure its correct.
        <footnote>
            <para>A useful read setting config on you hadoop cluster is Aaron
            Kimballs' <link
            xlink:ref="http://www.cloudera.com/blog/2009/03/configuration-parameters-what-can-you-just-ignore/">Configuration
            Parameters: What can you just ignore?</link></para>
          </footnote></para>

        <section xml:id="ulimit_ubuntu">
          <title><varname>ulimit</varname> on Ubuntu</title>

          <para>If you are on Ubuntu you will need to make the following
          changes:</para>

          <para>In the file <filename>/etc/security/limits.conf</filename> add
          a line like: <programlisting>hadoop  -       nofile  32768</programlisting>
          Replace <varname>hadoop</varname> with whatever user is running
          Hadoop and HBase. If you have separate users, you will need 2
          entries, one for each user.  In the same file set nproc hard and soft
          limits.  For example: <programlisting>hadoop soft/hard nproc 32000</programlisting>.</para>

          <para>In the file <filename>/etc/pam.d/common-session</filename> add
          as the last line in the file: <programlisting>session required  pam_limits.so</programlisting>
          Otherwise the changes in <filename>/etc/security/limits.conf</filename> won't be
          applied.</para>

          <para>Don't forget to log out and back in again for the changes to
          take effect!</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="windows">
        <title>Windows</title>

        <para>HBase has been little tested running on Windows. Running a
        production install of HBase on top of Windows is not
        recommended.</para>

        <para>If you are running HBase on Windows, you must install <link
        xlink:href="http://cygwin.com/">Cygwin</link> to have a *nix-like
        environment for the shell scripts. The full details are explained in
        the <link xlink:href="http://hbase.apache.org/cygwin.html">Windows
        Installation</link> guide. Also 
        <link xlink:href="http://search-hadoop.com/?q=hbase+windows&amp;fc_project=HBase&amp;fc_type=mail+_hash_+dev">search our user mailing list</link> to pick
        up latest fixes figured by Windows users.</para>
      </section>

    </section>   <!--  OS -->
    
    <section xml:id="hadoop">
        <title><link
        xlink:href="http://hadoop.apache.org">Hadoop</link><indexterm>
            <primary>Hadoop</primary>
          </indexterm></title>

          <para>
              This version of HBase will only run on <link
        xlink:href="http://hadoop.apache.org/common/releases.html">Hadoop
        0.20.x</link>. It will not run on hadoop 0.21.x (nor 0.22.x).
        HBase will lose data unless it is running on an HDFS that has a durable
        <code>sync</code>. Hadoop 0.20.2 and Hadoop 0.20.203.0 DO NOT have this attribute.
        Currently only the <link
        xlink:href="http://svn.apache.org/viewvc/hadoop/common/branches/branch-0.20-append/">branch-0.20-append</link>
        branch has this attribute<footnote>
            <para>See <link
            xlink:href="http://svn.apache.org/viewvc/hadoop/common/branches/branch-0.20-append/CHANGES.txt">CHANGES.txt</link>
            in branch-0.20-append to see list of patches involved adding
            append on the Hadoop 0.20 branch.</para>
          </footnote>. No official releases have been made from the branch-0.20-append branch up
        to now so you will have to build your own Hadoop from the tip of this
        branch.  Michael Noll has written a detailed blog,
        <link xlink:href="http://www.michael-noll.com/blog/2011/04/14/building-an-hadoop-0-20-x-version-for-hbase-0-90-2/">Building
        an Hadoop 0.20.x version for HBase 0.90.2</link>, on how to build an
        Hadoop from branch-0.20-append.  Recommended.</para>

        <para>Or rather than build your own, you could use Cloudera's <link
        xlink:href="http://archive.cloudera.com/docs/">CDH3</link>. CDH has
        the 0.20-append patches needed to add a durable sync (CDH3 betas will
        suffice; b2, b3, or b4).</para>

        <para>Because HBase depends on Hadoop, it bundles an instance of the
        Hadoop jar under its <filename>lib</filename> directory. The bundled
        Hadoop was made from the Apache branch-0.20-append branch at the time
        of the HBase's release.  The bundled jar is ONLY for use in standalone mode.
        In distributed mode, it is <emphasis>critical</emphasis> that the version of Hadoop that is out
        on your cluster match what is under HBase.  Replace the hadoop jar found in the HBase
        <filename>lib</filename> directory with the hadoop jar you are running on
        your cluster to avoid version mismatch issues. Make sure you
        replace the jar in HBase everywhere on your cluster.  Hadoop version
        mismatch issues have various manifestations but often all looks like
        its hung up.</para>

       <section xml:id="hadoop.security">
          <title>Hadoop Security</title>
          <para>HBase will run on any Hadoop 0.20.x that incorporates Hadoop
          security features -- e.g. Y! 0.20S or CDH3B3 -- as long as you do as
          suggested above and replace the Hadoop jar that ships with HBase
          with the secure version.</para>
       </section>
           
       <section xml:id="dfs.datanode.max.xcievers">
        <title><varname>dfs.datanode.max.xcievers</varname><indexterm>
            <primary>xcievers</primary>
          </indexterm></title>

        <para>An Hadoop HDFS datanode has an upper bound on the number of
        files that it will serve at any one time. The upper bound parameter is
        called <varname>xcievers</varname> (yes, this is misspelled). Again,
        before doing any loading, make sure you have configured Hadoop's
        <filename>conf/hdfs-site.xml</filename> setting the
        <varname>xceivers</varname> value to at least the following:
        <programlisting>
      &lt;property&gt;
        &lt;name&gt;dfs.datanode.max.xcievers&lt;/name&gt;
        &lt;value&gt;4096&lt;/value&gt;
      &lt;/property&gt;
      </programlisting></para>

        <para>Be sure to restart your HDFS after making the above
        configuration.</para>

        <para>Not having this configuration in place makes for strange looking
        failures. Eventually you'll see a complain in the datanode logs
        complaining about the xcievers exceeded, but on the run up to this one
        manifestation is complaint about missing blocks. For example:
        <code>10/12/08 20:10:31 INFO hdfs.DFSClient: Could not obtain block
        blk_XXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXX_YYYYYYYY from any node:
        java.io.IOException: No live nodes contain current block. Will get new
        block locations from namenode and retry...</code>
        <footnote><para>See <link xlink:href="http://ccgtech.blogspot.com/2010/02/hadoop-hdfs-deceived-by-xciever.html">Hadoop HDFS: Deceived by Xciever</link> for an informative rant on xceivering.</para></footnote></para>
      </section>
     
     </section>    <!--  hadoop -->

    <section xml:id="standalone_dist">
      <title>HBase run modes: Standalone and Distributed</title>

      <para>HBase has two run modes: <xref linkend="standalone" /> and <xref linkend="distributed" />. Out of the box, HBase runs in
      standalone mode. To set up a distributed deploy, you will need to
      configure HBase by editing files in the HBase <filename>conf</filename>
      directory.</para>

      <para>Whatever your mode, you will need to edit
      <code>conf/hbase-env.sh</code> to tell HBase which
      <command>java</command> to use. In this file you set HBase environment
      variables such as the heapsize and other options for the
      <application>JVM</application>, the preferred location for log files,
      etc. Set <varname>JAVA_HOME</varname> to point at the root of your
      <command>java</command> install.</para>

      <section xml:id="standalone">
        <title>Standalone HBase</title>

        <para>This is the default mode. Standalone mode is what is described
            in the <xref linkend="quickstart" /> section. In
        standalone mode, HBase does not use HDFS -- it uses the local
        filesystem instead -- and it runs all HBase daemons and a local
        ZooKeeper all up in the same JVM. Zookeeper binds to a well known port
        so clients may talk to HBase.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="distributed">
        <title>Distributed</title>

        <para>Distributed mode can be subdivided into distributed but all
        daemons run on a single node -- a.k.a
        <emphasis>pseudo-distributed</emphasis>-- and
        <emphasis>fully-distributed</emphasis> where the daemons are spread
        across all nodes in the cluster <footnote>
            <para>The pseudo-distributed vs fully-distributed nomenclature
            comes from Hadoop.</para>
          </footnote>.</para>

        <para>Distributed modes require an instance of the <emphasis>Hadoop
        Distributed File System</emphasis> (HDFS). See the Hadoop <link
        xlink:href="http://hadoop.apache.org/common/docs/current/api/overview-summary.html#overview_description">
        requirements and instructions</link> for how to set up a HDFS. Before
        proceeding, ensure you have an appropriate, working HDFS.</para>

        <para>Below we describe the different distributed setups. Starting,
        verification and exploration of your install, whether a
        <emphasis>pseudo-distributed</emphasis> or
        <emphasis>fully-distributed</emphasis> configuration is described in a
        section that follows, <xref linkend="confirm" />. The same verification script applies to both
        deploy types.</para>

        <section xml:id="pseudo">
          <title>Pseudo-distributed</title>

          <para>A pseudo-distributed mode is simply a distributed mode run on
          a single host. Use this configuration testing and prototyping on
          HBase. Do not use this configuration for production nor for
          evaluating HBase performance.</para>

          <para>Once you have confirmed your HDFS setup, edit
          <filename>conf/hbase-site.xml</filename>. This is the file into
          which you add local customizations and overrides for
          <xreg linkend="hbase_default_configurations" /> and <xref linkend="hdfs_client_conf" />. Point HBase at the running Hadoop HDFS
          instance by setting the <varname>hbase.rootdir</varname> property.
          This property points HBase at the Hadoop filesystem instance to use.
          For example, adding the properties below to your
          <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename> says that HBase should use the
          <filename>/hbase</filename> directory in the HDFS whose namenode is
          at port 9000 on your local machine, and that it should run with one
          replica only (recommended for pseudo-distributed mode):</para>

          <programlisting>
&lt;configuration&gt;
  ...
  &lt;property&gt;
    &lt;name&gt;hbase.rootdir&lt;/name&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;hdfs://localhost:9000/hbase&lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;description&gt;The directory shared by RegionServers.
    &lt;/description&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;property&gt;
    &lt;name&gt;dfs.replication&lt;/name&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;1&lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;description&gt;The replication count for HLog and HFile storage. Should not be greater than HDFS datanode count.
    &lt;/description&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
  ...
&lt;/configuration&gt;
</programlisting>

          <note>
            <para>Let HBase create the <varname>hbase.rootdir</varname>
            directory. If you don't, you'll get warning saying HBase needs a
            migration run because the directory is missing files expected by
            HBase (it'll create them if you let it).</para>
          </note>

          <note>
            <para>Above we bind to <varname>localhost</varname>. This means
            that a remote client cannot connect. Amend accordingly, if you
            want to connect from a remote location.</para>
          </note>

          <para>Now skip to <xref linkend="confirm" /> for how to start and verify your
          pseudo-distributed install. <footnote>
              <para>See <link
              xlink:href="http://hbase.apache.org/pseudo-distributed.html">Pseudo-distributed
              mode extras</link> for notes on how to start extra Masters and
              RegionServers when running pseudo-distributed.</para>
            </footnote></para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="fully_dist">
          <title>Fully-distributed</title>

          <para>For running a fully-distributed operation on more than one
          host, make the following configurations. In
          <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>, add the property
          <varname>hbase.cluster.distributed</varname> and set it to
          <varname>true</varname> and point the HBase
          <varname>hbase.rootdir</varname> at the appropriate HDFS NameNode
          and location in HDFS where you would like HBase to write data. For
          example, if you namenode were running at namenode.example.org on
          port 9000 and you wanted to home your HBase in HDFS at
          <filename>/hbase</filename>, make the following
          configuration.</para>

          <programlisting>
&lt;configuration&gt;
  ...
  &lt;property&gt;
    &lt;name&gt;hbase.rootdir&lt;/name&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;hdfs://namenode.example.org:9000/hbase&lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;description&gt;The directory shared by RegionServers.
    &lt;/description&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;property&gt;
    &lt;name&gt;hbase.cluster.distributed&lt;/name&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;true&lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;description&gt;The mode the cluster will be in. Possible values are
      false: standalone and pseudo-distributed setups with managed Zookeeper
      true: fully-distributed with unmanaged Zookeeper Quorum (see hbase-env.sh)
    &lt;/description&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
  ...
&lt;/configuration&gt;
</programlisting>

          <section xml:id="regionserver">
            <title><filename>regionservers</filename></title>

            <para>In addition, a fully-distributed mode requires that you
            modify <filename>conf/regionservers</filename>. The
            <xref linkend="regionservers" /> file
            lists all hosts that you would have running
            <application>HRegionServer</application>s, one host per line (This
            file in HBase is like the Hadoop <filename>slaves</filename>
            file). All servers listed in this file will be started and stopped
            when HBase cluster start or stop is run.</para>
          </section>

          <section xml:id="hbase.zookeeper">
            <title>ZooKeeper and HBase</title>
            <para>See section <xref linkend="zookeeper"/> for ZooKeeper setup for HBase.</para>
          </section>

          <section xml:id="hdfs_client_conf">
            <title>HDFS Client Configuration</title>

            <para>Of note, if you have made <emphasis>HDFS client
            configuration</emphasis> on your Hadoop cluster -- i.e.
            configuration you want HDFS clients to use as opposed to
            server-side configurations -- HBase will not see this
            configuration unless you do one of the following:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Add a pointer to your <varname>HADOOP_CONF_DIR</varname>
                to the <varname>HBASE_CLASSPATH</varname> environment variable
                in <filename>hbase-env.sh</filename>.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Add a copy of <filename>hdfs-site.xml</filename> (or
                <filename>hadoop-site.xml</filename>) or, better, symlinks,
                under <filename>${HBASE_HOME}/conf</filename>, or</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>if only a small set of HDFS client configurations, add
                them to <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>An example of such an HDFS client configuration is
            <varname>dfs.replication</varname>. If for example, you want to
            run with a replication factor of 5, hbase will create files with
            the default of 3 unless you do the above to make the configuration
            available to HBase.</para>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="confirm">
        <title>Running and Confirming Your Installation</title>

         

        <para>Make sure HDFS is running first. Start and stop the Hadoop HDFS
        daemons by running <filename>bin/start-hdfs.sh</filename> over in the
        <varname>HADOOP_HOME</varname> directory. You can ensure it started
        properly by testing the <command>put</command> and
        <command>get</command> of files into the Hadoop filesystem. HBase does
        not normally use the mapreduce daemons. These do not need to be
        started.</para>

         

        <para><emphasis>If</emphasis> you are managing your own ZooKeeper,
        start it and confirm its running else, HBase will start up ZooKeeper
        for you as part of its start process.</para>

         

        <para>Start HBase with the following command:</para>

         

        <programlisting>bin/start-hbase.sh</programlisting>

         Run the above from the 

        <varname>HBASE_HOME</varname>

         directory. 

        <para>You should now have a running HBase instance. HBase logs can be
        found in the <filename>logs</filename> subdirectory. Check them out
        especially if HBase had trouble starting.</para>

         

        <para>HBase also puts up a UI listing vital attributes. By default its
        deployed on the Master host at port 60010 (HBase RegionServers listen
        on port 60020 by default and put up an informational http server at
        60030). If the Master were running on a host named
        <varname>master.example.org</varname> on the default port, to see the
        Master's homepage you'd point your browser at
        <filename>http://master.example.org:60010</filename>.</para>

         

    <para>Once HBase has started, see the <xref linkend="shell_exercises" /> for how to
        create tables, add data, scan your insertions, and finally disable and
        drop your tables.</para>

         

        <para>To stop HBase after exiting the HBase shell enter
        <programlisting>$ ./bin/stop-hbase.sh
stopping hbase...............</programlisting> Shutdown can take a moment to
        complete. It can take longer if your cluster is comprised of many
        machines. If you are running a distributed operation, be sure to wait
        until HBase has shut down completely before stopping the Hadoop
        daemons.</para>

         
      </section>
     </section>    <!--  run modes -->
    
     <section xml:id="zookeeper">
            <title>ZooKeeper<indexterm>
                <primary>ZooKeeper</primary>
              </indexterm></title>

            <para>A distributed HBase depends on a running ZooKeeper cluster.
            All participating nodes and clients need to be able to access the
            running ZooKeeper ensemble. HBase by default manages a ZooKeeper
            "cluster" for you. It will start and stop the ZooKeeper ensemble
            as part of the HBase start/stop process. You can also manage the
            ZooKeeper ensemble independent of HBase and just point HBase at
            the cluster it should use. To toggle HBase management of
            ZooKeeper, use the <varname>HBASE_MANAGES_ZK</varname> variable in
            <filename>conf/hbase-env.sh</filename>. This variable, which
            defaults to <varname>true</varname>, tells HBase whether to
            start/stop the ZooKeeper ensemble servers as part of HBase
            start/stop.</para>

            <para>When HBase manages the ZooKeeper ensemble, you can specify
            ZooKeeper configuration using its native
            <filename>zoo.cfg</filename> file, or, the easier option is to
            just specify ZooKeeper options directly in
            <filename>conf/hbase-site.xml</filename>. A ZooKeeper
            configuration option can be set as a property in the HBase
            <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename> XML configuration file by
            prefacing the ZooKeeper option name with
            <varname>hbase.zookeeper.property</varname>. For example, the
            <varname>clientPort</varname> setting in ZooKeeper can be changed
            by setting the
            <varname>hbase.zookeeper.property.clientPort</varname> property.
            For all default values used by HBase, including ZooKeeper
            configuration, see <xref linkend="hbase_default_configurations" />. Look for the
            <varname>hbase.zookeeper.property</varname> prefix <footnote>
                <para>For the full list of ZooKeeper configurations, see
                ZooKeeper's <filename>zoo.cfg</filename>. HBase does not ship
                with a <filename>zoo.cfg</filename> so you will need to browse
                the <filename>conf</filename> directory in an appropriate
                ZooKeeper download.</para>
              </footnote></para>

            <para>You must at least list the ensemble servers in
            <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename> using the
            <varname>hbase.zookeeper.quorum</varname> property. This property
            defaults to a single ensemble member at
            <varname>localhost</varname> which is not suitable for a fully
            distributed HBase. (It binds to the local machine only and remote
            clients will not be able to connect). <note xml:id="how_many_zks">
                <title>How many ZooKeepers should I run?</title>

                <para>You can run a ZooKeeper ensemble that comprises 1 node
                only but in production it is recommended that you run a
                ZooKeeper ensemble of 3, 5 or 7 machines; the more members an
                ensemble has, the more tolerant the ensemble is of host
                failures. Also, run an odd number of machines. There can be no
                quorum if the number of members is an even number. Give each
                ZooKeeper server around 1GB of RAM, and if possible, its own
                dedicated disk (A dedicated disk is the best thing you can do
                to ensure a performant ZooKeeper ensemble). For very heavily
                loaded clusters, run ZooKeeper servers on separate machines
                from RegionServers (DataNodes and TaskTrackers).</para>
              </note></para>

            <para>For example, to have HBase manage a ZooKeeper quorum on
            nodes <emphasis>rs{1,2,3,4,5}.example.com</emphasis>, bound to
            port 2222 (the default is 2181) ensure
            <varname>HBASE_MANAGE_ZK</varname> is commented out or set to
            <varname>true</varname> in <filename>conf/hbase-env.sh</filename>
            and then edit <filename>conf/hbase-site.xml</filename> and set
            <varname>hbase.zookeeper.property.clientPort</varname> and
            <varname>hbase.zookeeper.quorum</varname>. You should also set
            <varname>hbase.zookeeper.property.dataDir</varname> to other than
            the default as the default has ZooKeeper persist data under
            <filename>/tmp</filename> which is often cleared on system
            restart. In the example below we have ZooKeeper persist to
            <filename>/user/local/zookeeper</filename>. <programlisting>
  &lt;configuration&gt;
    ...
    &lt;property&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;hbase.zookeeper.property.clientPort&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;value&gt;2222&lt;/value&gt;
      &lt;description&gt;Property from ZooKeeper's config zoo.cfg.
      The port at which the clients will connect.
      &lt;/description&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;property&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;hbase.zookeeper.quorum&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;value&gt;rs1.example.com,rs2.example.com,rs3.example.com,rs4.example.com,rs5.example.com&lt;/value&gt;
      &lt;description&gt;Comma separated list of servers in the ZooKeeper Quorum.
      For example, "host1.mydomain.com,host2.mydomain.com,host3.mydomain.com".
      By default this is set to localhost for local and pseudo-distributed modes
      of operation. For a fully-distributed setup, this should be set to a full
      list of ZooKeeper quorum servers. If HBASE_MANAGES_ZK is set in hbase-env.sh
      this is the list of servers which we will start/stop ZooKeeper on.
      &lt;/description&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;property&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;hbase.zookeeper.property.dataDir&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;value&gt;/usr/local/zookeeper&lt;/value&gt;
      &lt;description&gt;Property from ZooKeeper's config zoo.cfg.
      The directory where the snapshot is stored.
      &lt;/description&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
    ...
  &lt;/configuration&gt;</programlisting></para>

            <section>
              <title>Using existing ZooKeeper ensemble</title>

              <para>To point HBase at an existing ZooKeeper cluster, one that
              is not managed by HBase, set <varname>HBASE_MANAGES_ZK</varname>
              in <filename>conf/hbase-env.sh</filename> to false
              <programlisting>
  ...
  # Tell HBase whether it should manage it's own instance of Zookeeper or not.
  export HBASE_MANAGES_ZK=false</programlisting> Next set ensemble locations
              and client port, if non-standard, in
              <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>, or add a suitably
              configured <filename>zoo.cfg</filename> to HBase's
              <filename>CLASSPATH</filename>. HBase will prefer the
              configuration found in <filename>zoo.cfg</filename> over any
              settings in <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>.</para>

              <para>When HBase manages ZooKeeper, it will start/stop the
              ZooKeeper servers as a part of the regular start/stop scripts.
              If you would like to run ZooKeeper yourself, independent of
              HBase start/stop, you would do the following</para>

              <programlisting>
${HBASE_HOME}/bin/hbase-daemons.sh {start,stop} zookeeper
</programlisting>

              <para>Note that you can use HBase in this manner to spin up a
              ZooKeeper cluster, unrelated to HBase. Just make sure to set
              <varname>HBASE_MANAGES_ZK</varname> to <varname>false</varname>
              if you want it to stay up across HBase restarts so that when
              HBase shuts down, it doesn't take ZooKeeper down with it.</para>

              <para>For more information about running a distinct ZooKeeper
              cluster, see the ZooKeeper <link
              xlink:href="http://hadoop.apache.org/zookeeper/docs/current/zookeeperStarted.html">Getting
              Started Guide</link>.  Additionally, see the <link xlink:href="http://wiki.apache.org/hadoop/ZooKeeper/FAQ#A7">ZooKeeper Wiki</link> or the 
          <link xlink:href="http://zookeeper.apache.org/doc/r3.3.3/zookeeperAdmin.html#sc_zkMulitServerSetup">ZooKeeper documentation</link> 
          for more information on ZooKeeper sizing.
            </para>
            </section>
     </section>     <!--  zookeeper -->        
    
    
    <section xml:id="config.files">    
         <title>Configuration Files</title>
         
    <section xml:id="hbase.site">
    <title><filename>hbase-site.xml</filename> and <filename>hbase-default.xml</filename></title>
    <para>Just as in Hadoop where you add site-specific HDFS configuration
    to the <filename>hdfs-site.xml</filename> file,
    for HBase, site specific customizations go into
    the file <filename>conf/hbase-site.xml</filename>.
    For the list of configurable properties, see
    <xref linkend="hbase_default_configurations" />
    below or view the raw <filename>hbase-default.xml</filename>
    source file in the HBase source code at
    <filename>src/main/resources</filename>.
    </para>
    <para>
    Not all configuration options make it out to
    <filename>hbase-default.xml</filename>.  Configuration
    that it is thought rare anyone would change can exist only
    in code; the only way to turn up such configurations is
    via a reading of the source code itself.
    </para>
      <para>
      Currently, changes here will require a cluster restart for HBase to notice the change.
      </para>
    <!--The file hbase-default.xml is generated as part of
    the build of the hbase site.  See the hbase pom.xml.
    The generated file is a docbook section with a glossary
    in it-->
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      href="../../target/site/hbase-default.xml" />
    </section>

      <section xml:id="hbase.env.sh">
      <title><filename>hbase-env.sh</filename></title>
      <para>Set HBase environment variables in this file.
      Examples include options to pass the JVM on start of
      an HBase daemon such as heap size and garbarge collector configs.
      You can also set configurations for HBase configuration, log directories,
      niceness, ssh options, where to locate process pid files,
      etc. Open the file at
      <filename>conf/hbase-env.sh</filename> and peruse its content.
      Each option is fairly well documented.  Add your own environment
      variables here if you want them read by HBase daemons on startup.</para>
      <para>
      Changes here will require a cluster restart for HBase to notice the change.
      </para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="log4j">
      <title><filename>log4j.properties</filename></title>
      <para>Edit this file to change rate at which HBase files
      are rolled and to change the level at which HBase logs messages.
      </para>
      <para>
      Changes here will require a cluster restart for HBase to notice the change
      though log levels can be changed for particular daemons via the HBase UI.
      </para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="client_dependencies"><title>Client configuration and dependencies connecting to an HBase cluster</title>
       <para>
          Since the HBase Master may move around, clients bootstrap by looking to ZooKeeper for
          current critical locations.  ZooKeeper is where all these values are kept.  Thus clients
          require the location of the ZooKeeper ensemble information before they can do anything else.
          Usually this the ensemble location is kept out in the <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename> and
          is picked up by the client from the <varname>CLASSPATH</varname>.</para>

        <para>If you are configuring an IDE to run a HBase client, you should
            include the <filename>conf/</filename> directory on your classpath so
            <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename> settings can be found (or
            add <filename>src/test/resources</filename> to pick up the hbase-site.xml
            used by tests).
      </para>
      <para>
          Minimally, a client of HBase needs the hbase, hadoop, log4j, commons-logging, commons-lang,
          and ZooKeeper jars in its <varname>CLASSPATH</varname> connecting to a cluster.
      </para>
        <para>
          An example basic <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename> for client only
          might look as follows:
          <programlisting><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="configuration.xsl"?>
<configuration>
  <property>
    <name>hbase.zookeeper.quorum</name>
    <value>example1,example2,example3</value>
    <description>The directory shared by region servers.
    </description>
  </property>
</configuration>
]]></programlisting>
        </para>
        
        <section xml:id="java.client.config">
        <title>Java client configuration</title>
        <para>The configuration used by a Java client is kept
        in an <link xlink:href="http://hbase.apache.org/apidocs/org/apache/hadoop/hbase/HBaseConfiguration">HBaseConfiguration</link> instance.
        The factory method on HBaseConfiguration, <code>HBaseConfiguration.create();</code>,
        on invocation, will read in the content of the first <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename> found on
        the client's <varname>CLASSPATH</varname>, if one is present
        (Invocation will also factor in any <filename>hbase-default.xml</filename> found;
        an hbase-default.xml ships inside the <filename>hbase.X.X.X.jar</filename>). 
        It is also possible to specify configuration directly without having to read from a
        <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>.  For example, to set the ZooKeeper
        ensemble for the cluster programmatically do as follows:
        <programlisting>Configuration config = HBaseConfiguration.create();
config.set("hbase.zookeeper.quorum", "localhost");  // Here we are running zookeeper locally</programlisting>    
        If multiple ZooKeeper instances make up your ZooKeeper ensemble,
        they may be specified in a comma-separated list (just as in the <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename> file).
        This populated <classname>Configuration</classname> instance can then be passed to an 
        <link xlink:href="http://hbase.apache.org/apidocs/org/apache/hadoop/hbase/client/HTable.html">HTable</link>,
        and so on.
        </para>
       </section>
        </section>

      </section>  <!--  config files -->
      
      <section xml:id="example_config">
      <title>Example Configurations</title>

      <section>
        <title>Basic Distributed HBase Install</title>

        <para>Here is an example basic configuration for a distributed ten
        node cluster. The nodes are named <varname>example0</varname>,
        <varname>example1</varname>, etc., through node
        <varname>example9</varname> in this example. The HBase Master and the
        HDFS namenode are running on the node <varname>example0</varname>.
        RegionServers run on nodes
        <varname>example1</varname>-<varname>example9</varname>. A 3-node
        ZooKeeper ensemble runs on <varname>example1</varname>,
        <varname>example2</varname>, and <varname>example3</varname> on the
        default ports. ZooKeeper data is persisted to the directory
        <filename>/export/zookeeper</filename>. Below we show what the main
        configuration files -- <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>,
        <filename>regionservers</filename>, and
        <filename>hbase-env.sh</filename> -- found in the HBase
        <filename>conf</filename> directory might look like.</para>

        <section xml:id="hbase_site">
          <title><filename>hbase-site.xml</filename></title>

          <programlisting>

&lt;?xml version="1.0"?&gt;
&lt;?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="configuration.xsl"?&gt;
&lt;configuration&gt;
  &lt;property&gt;
    &lt;name&gt;hbase.zookeeper.quorum&lt;/name&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;example1,example2,example3&lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;description&gt;The directory shared by RegionServers.
    &lt;/description&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;property&gt;
    &lt;name&gt;hbase.zookeeper.property.dataDir&lt;/name&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;/export/zookeeper&lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;description&gt;Property from ZooKeeper's config zoo.cfg.
    The directory where the snapshot is stored.
    &lt;/description&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;property&gt;
    &lt;name&gt;hbase.rootdir&lt;/name&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;hdfs://example0:9000/hbase&lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;description&gt;The directory shared by RegionServers.
    &lt;/description&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;property&gt;
    &lt;name&gt;hbase.cluster.distributed&lt;/name&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;true&lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;description&gt;The mode the cluster will be in. Possible values are
      false: standalone and pseudo-distributed setups with managed Zookeeper
      true: fully-distributed with unmanaged Zookeeper Quorum (see hbase-env.sh)
    &lt;/description&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/configuration&gt;

    </programlisting>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="regionservers">
          <title><filename>regionservers</filename></title>

          <para>In this file you list the nodes that will run RegionServers.
          In our case we run RegionServers on all but the head node
          <varname>example1</varname> which is carrying the HBase Master and
          the HDFS namenode</para>

          <programlisting>
    example1
    example3
    example4
    example5
    example6
    example7
    example8
    example9
    </programlisting>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="hbase_env">
          <title><filename>hbase-env.sh</filename></title>

          <para>Below we use a <command>diff</command> to show the differences
          from default in the <filename>hbase-env.sh</filename> file. Here we
          are setting the HBase heap to be 4G instead of the default
          1G.</para>

          <programlisting>
    
$ git diff hbase-env.sh
diff --git a/conf/hbase-env.sh b/conf/hbase-env.sh
index e70ebc6..96f8c27 100644
--- a/conf/hbase-env.sh
+++ b/conf/hbase-env.sh
@@ -31,7 +31,7 @@ export JAVA_HOME=/usr/lib//jvm/java-6-sun/
 # export HBASE_CLASSPATH=
 
 # The maximum amount of heap to use, in MB. Default is 1000.
-# export HBASE_HEAPSIZE=1000
+export HBASE_HEAPSIZE=4096
 
 # Extra Java runtime options.
 # Below are what we set by default.  May only work with SUN JVM.

    </programlisting>

          <para>Use <command>rsync</command> to copy the content of the
          <filename>conf</filename> directory to all nodes of the
          cluster.</para>
        </section>
      </section>
     </section>       <!-- example config -->
      
      
      <section xml:id="important_configurations">
      <title>The Important Configurations</title>
      <para>Below we list what the <emphasis>important</emphasis>
      Configurations.  We've divided this section into
      required configuration and worth-a-look recommended configs.
      </para>


      <section xml:id="required_configuration"><title>Required Configurations</title>
          <para>Review the <xref linkend="os" /> and <xref linkend="hadoop" /> sections.
      </para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="recommended_configurations"><title>Recommended Configuations</title>
          <section xml:id="zookeeper.session.timeout"><title><varname>zookeeper.session.timeout</varname></title>
          <para>The default timeout is three minutes (specified in milliseconds). This means
              that if a server crashes, it will be three minutes before the Master notices
              the crash and starts recovery. You might like to tune the timeout down to
              a minute or even less so the Master notices failures the sooner.
              Before changing this value, be sure you have your JVM garbage collection
              configuration under control otherwise, a long garbage collection that lasts
              beyond the ZooKeeper session timeout will take out
              your RegionServer (You might be fine with this -- you probably want recovery to start
          on the server if a RegionServer has been in GC for a long period of time).</para> 

      <para>To change this configuration, edit <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>,
          copy the changed file around the cluster and restart.</para>

          <para>We set this value high to save our having to field noob questions up on the mailing lists asking
              why a RegionServer went down during a massive import.  The usual cause is that their JVM is untuned and
              they are running into long GC pauses.  Our thinking is that
              while users are  getting familiar with HBase, we'd save them having to know all of its
              intricacies.  Later when they've built some confidence, then they can play
              with configuration such as this.
          </para>
      </section>
          <section xml:id="zookeeper.instances"><title>Number of ZooKeeper Instances</title>
          <para>See <xref linkend="zookeeper"/>.
          </para>
      </section>
          <section xml:id="hbase.regionserver.handler.count"><title><varname>hbase.regionserver.handler.count</varname></title>
          <para>
          This setting defines the number of threads that are kept open to answer
          incoming requests to user tables. The default of 10 is rather low in order to
          prevent users from killing their region servers when using large write buffers
          with a high number of concurrent clients. The rule of thumb is to keep this
          number low when the payload per request approaches the MB (big puts, scans using
          a large cache) and high when the payload is small (gets, small puts, ICVs, deletes).
          </para>
          <para>
          It is safe to set that number to the
          maximum number of incoming clients if their payload is small, the typical example
          being a cluster that serves a website since puts aren't typically buffered
          and most of the operations are gets.
          </para>
          <para>
          The reason why it is dangerous to keep this setting high is that the aggregate
          size of all the puts that are currently happening in a region server may impose
          too much pressure on its memory, or even trigger an OutOfMemoryError. A region server
          running on low memory will trigger its JVM's garbage collector to run more frequently
          up to a point where GC pauses become noticeable (the reason being that all the memory
          used to keep all the requests' payloads cannot be trashed, no matter how hard the
          garbage collector tries). After some time, the overall cluster
          throughput is affected since every request that hits that region server will take longer,
          which exacerbates the problem even more.
          </para>
          </section>
      <section xml:id="big_memory">
        <title>Configuration for large memory machines</title>
        <para>
          HBase ships with a reasonable, conservative configuration that will
          work on nearly all
          machine types that people might want to test with. If you have larger
          machines -- HBase has 8G and larger heap -- you might the following configuration options helpful.
          TODO.
        </para>

      </section>

      <section xml:id="config.compression">
      <title>Compression</title>
      <para>You should consider enabling ColumnFamily compression.  There are several options that are near-frictionless and in most all cases boost
      performance by reducing the size of StoreFiles and thus reducing I/O.
      </para>
      <para>See <xref linkend="compression" /> for more information.</para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="bigger.regions">
      <title>Bigger Regions</title>
      <para>
      Consider going to larger regions to cut down on the total number of regions
      on your cluster. Generally less Regions to manage makes for a smoother running
      cluster (You can always later manually split the big Regions should one prove
      hot and you want to spread the request load over the cluster).  By default,
      regions are 256MB in size.  You could run with
      1G.  Some run with even larger regions; 4G or even larger.  Adjust
      <code>hbase.hregion.max.filesize</code> in your <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>.
      </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="disable.splitting">
      <title>Managed Splitting</title>
      <para>
      Rather than let HBase auto-split your Regions, manage the splitting manually
      <footnote><para>What follows is taken from the javadoc at the head of
      the <classname>org.apache.hadoop.hbase.util.RegionSplitter</classname> tool
      added to HBase post-0.90.0 release.
      </para>
      </footnote>.
 With growing amounts of data, splits will continually be needed. Since
 you always know exactly what regions you have, long-term debugging and
 profiling is much easier with manual splits. It is hard to trace the logs to
 understand region level problems if it keeps splitting and getting renamed.
 Data offlining bugs + unknown number of split regions == oh crap! If an
 <classname>HLog</classname> or <classname>StoreFile</classname>
 was mistakenly unprocessed by HBase due to a weird bug and
 you notice it a day or so later, you can be assured that the regions
 specified in these files are the same as the current regions and you have
 less headaches trying to restore/replay your data.
 You can finely tune your compaction algorithm. With roughly uniform data
 growth, it's easy to cause split / compaction storms as the regions all
 roughly hit the same data size at the same time. With manual splits, you can
 let staggered, time-based major compactions spread out your network IO load.
      </para>
      <para>
 How do I turn off automatic splitting? Automatic splitting is determined by the configuration value
 <code>hbase.hregion.max.filesize</code>. It is not recommended that you set this
 to <varname>Long.MAX_VALUE</varname> in case you forget about manual splits. A suggested setting
 is 100GB, which would result in > 1hr major compactions if reached.
 </para>
 <para>What's the optimal number of pre-split regions to create?
 Mileage will vary depending upon your application.
 You could start low with 10 pre-split regions / server and watch as data grows
 over time. It's better to err on the side of too little regions and rolling split later.
 A more complicated answer is that this depends upon the largest storefile
 in your region. With a growing data size, this will get larger over time. You
 want the largest region to be just big enough that the <classname>Store</classname> compact
 selection algorithm only compacts it due to a timed major. If you don't, your
 cluster can be prone to compaction storms as the algorithm decides to run
 major compactions on a large series of regions all at once. Note that
 compaction storms are due to the uniform data growth, not the manual split
 decision.
 </para>
<para> If you pre-split your regions too thin, you can increase the major compaction
interval by configuring <varname>HConstants.MAJOR_COMPACTION_PERIOD</varname>. If your data size
grows too large, use the (post-0.90.0 HBase) <classname>org.apache.hadoop.hbase.util.RegionSplitter</classname>
script to perform a network IO safe rolling split
of all regions.
</para>
      </section>

      </section>

      </section>

  </chapter>
