<?xml version="1.0"?>
  <chapter xml:id="getting_started"
      version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
      xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Getting Started</title>
    <section >
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <para>
          <link linkend="quickstart">Quick Start</link> will get you up and running
          on a single-node instance of HBase using the local filesystem.
          The <link linkend="notsoquick">Not-so-quick Start Guide</link> 
          describes setup of HBase in distributed mode running on top of HDFS.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="quickstart">
      <title>Quick Start</title>

          <para>This guide describes setup of a standalone HBase
              instance that uses the local filesystem.  It leads you
              through creating a table, inserting rows via the
          <link linkend="shell">HBase Shell</link>, and then cleaning up and shutting
          down your standalone HBase instance.
          The below exercise should take no more than
          ten minutes (not including download time).
      </para>
          
          <section>
            <title>Download and unpack the latest stable release.</title>

            <para>Choose a download site from this list of <link
            xlink:href="http://www.apache.org/dyn/closer.cgi/hbase/">Apache
            Download Mirrors</link>. Click on suggested top link. This will take you to a
            mirror of <emphasis>HBase Releases</emphasis>. Click on
            the folder named <filename>stable</filename> and then download the
            file that ends in <filename>.tar.gz</filename> to your local filesystem;
            e.g. <filename>hbase-<?eval ${project.version}?>.tar.gz</filename>.</para>

            <para>Decompress and untar your download and then change into the
            unpacked directory.</para>

            <para><programlisting>$ tar xfz hbase-<?eval ${project.version}?>.tar.gz
$ cd hbase-<?eval ${project.version}?>
</programlisting></para>

<para>
   At this point, you are ready to start HBase. But before starting it,
   you might want to edit <filename>conf/hbase-site.xml</filename>
   and set the directory you want HBase to write to,
   <varname>hbase.rootdir</varname>.
   <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="configuration.xsl"?>
<configuration>
  <property>
    <name>hbase.rootdir</name>
    <value>file:///DIRECTORY/hbase</value>
  </property>
</configuration>
]]>
</programlisting>
Replace <varname>DIRECTORY</varname> in the above with a path to a directory where you want
HBase to store its data.  By default, <varname>hbase.rootdir</varname> is
set to <filename>/tmp/hbase-${user.name}</filename> 
which means you'll lose all your data whenever your server reboots
(Most operating systems clear <filename>/tmp</filename> on restart).
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="start_hbase">
<title>Start HBase</title>

            <para>Now start HBase:<programlisting>$ ./bin/start-hbase.sh
starting Master, logging to logs/hbase-user-master-example.org.out</programlisting></para>

            <para>You should
            now have a running standalone HBase instance. In standalone mode, HBase runs
            all daemons in the the one JVM; i.e. both the HBase and ZooKeeper daemons.
            HBase logs can be found in the <filename>logs</filename> subdirectory. Check them
            out especially if HBase had trouble starting.</para>

            <note>
            <title>Is <application>java</application> installed?</title>
            <para>All of the above presumes a 1.6 version of Oracle
            <application>java</application> is installed on your
            machine and available on your path; i.e. when you type
            <application>java</application>, you see output that describes the options
            the java program takes (HBase requires java 6).  If this is
            not the case, HBase will not start.
            Install java, edit <filename>conf/hbase-env.sh</filename>, uncommenting the
            <envar>JAVA_HOME</envar> line pointing it to your java install.  Then,
            retry the steps above.</para>
            </note>
            </section>
            

      <section xml:id="shell_exercises">
          <title>Shell Exercises</title>
            <para>Connect to your running HBase via the 
          <link linkend="shell">HBase Shell</link>.</para>

            <para><programlisting>$ ./bin/hbase shell
HBase Shell; enter 'help&lt;RETURN&gt;' for list of supported commands.
Type "exit&lt;RETURN&gt;" to leave the HBase Shell
Version: 0.89.20100924, r1001068, Fri Sep 24 13:55:42 PDT 2010

hbase(main):001:0&gt; </programlisting></para>

            <para>Type <command>help</command> and then <command>&lt;RETURN&gt;</command>
            to see a listing of shell
            commands and options. Browse at least the paragraphs at the end of
            the help emission for the gist of how variables and command
            arguments are entered into the
            HBase shell; in particular note how table names, rows, and
            columns, etc., must be quoted.</para>

            <para>Create a table named <varname>test</varname> with a single
            <link linkend="columnfamily">column family</link> named <varname>cf</varname>.
            Verify its creation by listing all tables and then insert some
            values.</para>
            <para><programlisting>hbase(main):003:0&gt; create 'test', 'cf'
0 row(s) in 1.2200 seconds
hbase(main):003:0&gt; list 'table'
test
1 row(s) in 0.0550 seconds
hbase(main):004:0&gt; put 'test', 'row1', 'cf:a', 'value1'
0 row(s) in 0.0560 seconds
hbase(main):005:0&gt; put 'test', 'row2', 'cf:b', 'value2'
0 row(s) in 0.0370 seconds
hbase(main):006:0&gt; put 'test', 'row3', 'cf:c', 'value3'
0 row(s) in 0.0450 seconds</programlisting></para>

            <para>Above we inserted 3 values, one at a time. The first insert is at
            <varname>row1</varname>, column <varname>cf:a</varname> with a value of
            <varname>value1</varname>.
            Columns in HBase are comprised of a
            <link linkend="columnfamily">column family</link> prefix
            -- <varname>cf</varname> in this example -- followed by
            a colon and then a column qualifier suffix (<varname>a</varname> in this case).
            </para>

            <para>Verify the data insert.</para>

            <para>Run a scan of the table by doing the following</para>

            <para><programlisting>hbase(main):007:0&gt; scan 'test'
ROW        COLUMN+CELL
row1       column=cf:a, timestamp=1288380727188, value=value1
row2       column=cf:b, timestamp=1288380738440, value=value2
row3       column=cf:c, timestamp=1288380747365, value=value3
3 row(s) in 0.0590 seconds</programlisting></para>

            <para>Get a single row as follows</para>

            <para><programlisting>hbase(main):008:0&gt; get 'test', 'row1'
COLUMN      CELL
cf:a        timestamp=1288380727188, value=value1
1 row(s) in 0.0400 seconds</programlisting></para>

            <para>Now, disable and drop your table. This will clean up all
            done above.</para>

            <para><programlisting>hbase(main):012:0&gt; disable 'test'
0 row(s) in 1.0930 seconds
hbase(main):013:0&gt; drop 'test'
0 row(s) in 0.0770 seconds </programlisting></para>

            <para>Exit the shell by typing exit.</para>

            <para><programlisting>hbase(main):014:0&gt; exit</programlisting></para>
            </section>

          <section xml:id="stopping">
          <title>Stopping HBase</title>
            <para>Stop your hbase instance by running the stop script.</para>

            <para><programlisting>$ ./bin/stop-hbase.sh
stopping hbase...............</programlisting></para>
          </section>

      <section><title>Where to go next
      </title>
      <para>The above described standalone setup is good for testing and experiments only.
      Move on to the next section, the <link linkend="notsoquick">Not-so-quick Start Guide</link>
      where we'll go into depth on the different HBase run modes, requirements and critical
      configurations needed setting up a distributed HBase deploy.
      </para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="notsoquick">
      <title>Not-so-quick Start Guide</title>
      
      <section xml:id="requirements"><title>Requirements</title>
      <para>HBase has the following requirements.  Please read the
      section below carefully and ensure that all requirements have been
      satisfied.  Failure to do so will cause you (and us) grief debugging
      strange errors and/or data loss.
      </para>

  <section xml:id="java"><title>java</title>
<para>
  Just like Hadoop, HBase requires java 6 from <link xlink:href="http://www.java.com/download/">Oracle</link>.
Usually you'll want to use the latest version available except the problematic u18  (u22 is the latest version as of this writing).</para>
</section>

  <section xml:id="hadoop"><title><link xlink:href="http://hadoop.apache.org">hadoop</link><indexterm><primary>Hadoop</primary></indexterm></title>
<para>This version of HBase will only run on <link xlink:href="http://hadoop.apache.org/common/releases.html">Hadoop 0.20.x</link>.
    It will not run on hadoop 0.21.x (nor 0.22.x) as of this writing.
    HBase will lose data unless it is running on an HDFS that has a
    durable <code>sync</code>.  Currently only the
    <link xlink:href="http://svn.apache.org/viewvc/hadoop/common/branches/branch-0.20-append/">branch-0.20-append</link>
    branch has this attribute
    <footnote>
    <para>
 See <link xlink:href="http://svn.apache.org/viewvc/hadoop/common/branches/branch-0.20-append/CHANGES.txt">CHANGES.txt</link>
 in branch-0.20-append to see list of patches involved adding append on the Hadoop 0.20 branch.
 </para>
 </footnote>.
    No official releases have been made from this branch up to now
    so you will have to build your own Hadoop from the tip of this branch.
    Scroll down in the Hadoop <link xlink:href="http://wiki.apache.org/hadoop/HowToRelease">How To Release</link> to the section
    <emphasis>Build Requirements</emphasis> for instruction on how to build Hadoop.
    </para>

 <para>
 Or rather than build your own, you could use
 Cloudera's <link xlink:href="http://archive.cloudera.com/docs/">CDH3</link>.
 CDH has the 0.20-append patches needed to add a durable sync (CDH3 is still in beta.
 Either CDH3b2 or CDH3b3 will suffice).
 </para>

 <para>Because HBase depends on Hadoop, it bundles an instance of
 the Hadoop jar under its <filename>lib</filename> directory.
 The bundled Hadoop was made from the Apache branch-0.20-append branch
 at the time of this HBase's release.
 It is <emphasis>critical</emphasis> that the version of Hadoop that is
 out on your cluster matches what is Hbase match.  Replace the hadoop
 jar found in the HBase <filename>lib</filename> directory with the
 hadoop jar you are running out on your cluster to avoid version mismatch issues.
 Make sure you replace the jar all over your cluster.
 For example, versions of CDH do not have HDFS-724 whereas
 Hadoops branch-0.20-append branch does have HDFS-724. This
 patch changes the RPC version because protocol was changed.
 Version mismatch issues have various manifestations but often all looks like its hung up.
 </para>

 <note><title>Can I just replace the jar in Hadoop 0.20.2 tarball with the <emphasis>sync</emphasis>-supporting Hadoop jar found in HBase?</title>
 <para>
 You could do this.  It works going by a recent posting up on the
 <link xlink:href="http://www.apacheserver.net/Using-Hadoop-bundled-in-lib-directory-HBase-at1136240.htm">mailing list</link>.
 </para>
 </note>
 <note><title>Hadoop Security</title>
     <para>HBase will run on any Hadoop 0.20.x that incorporates Hadoop security features -- e.g. Y! 0.20S or CDH3B3 -- as long
         as you do as suggested above and replace the Hadoop jar that ships with HBase with the secure version.
  </para>
  </note>

  </section>
<section xml:id="ssh"> <title>ssh</title>
<para><command>ssh</command> must be installed and <command>sshd</command> must
be running to use Hadoop's scripts to manage remote Hadoop and HBase daemons.
   You must be able to ssh to all nodes, including your local node, using passwordless login (Google "ssh passwordless login").
  </para>
</section>
  <section xml:id="dns"><title>DNS</title>
    <para>HBase uses the local hostname to self-report it's IP address. Both forward and reverse DNS resolving should work.</para>
    <para>If your machine has multiple interfaces, HBase will use the interface that the primary hostname resolves to.</para>
    <para>If this is insufficient, you can set <varname>hbase.regionserver.dns.interface</varname> to indicate the primary interface.
    This only works if your cluster
    configuration is consistent and every host has the same network interface configuration.</para>
    <para>Another alternative is setting <varname>hbase.regionserver.dns.nameserver</varname> to choose a different nameserver than the
    system wide default.</para>
</section>
  <section xml:id="ntp"><title>NTP</title>
<para>
    The clocks on cluster members should be in basic alignments. Some skew is tolerable but
    wild skew could generate odd behaviors. Run <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Network_Time_Protocol">NTP</link>
    on your cluster, or an equivalent.
  </para>
    <para>If you are having problems querying data, or "weird" cluster operations, check system time!</para>
</section>


      <section xml:id="ulimit">
      <title><varname>ulimit</varname><indexterm><primary>ulimit</primary></indexterm></title>
      <para>HBase is a database, it uses a lot of files at the same time.
      The default ulimit -n of 1024 on *nix systems is insufficient.
      Any significant amount of loading will lead you to 
      <link xlink:href="http://wiki.apache.org/hadoop/Hbase/FAQ#A6">FAQ: Why do I see "java.io.IOException...(Too many open files)" in my logs?</link>.
      You may also notice errors such as
      <programlisting>
      2010-04-06 03:04:37,542 INFO org.apache.hadoop.hdfs.DFSClient: Exception increateBlockOutputStream java.io.EOFException
      2010-04-06 03:04:37,542 INFO org.apache.hadoop.hdfs.DFSClient: Abandoning block blk_-6935524980745310745_1391901
      </programlisting>
      Do yourself a favor and change the upper bound on the number of file descriptors.
      Set it to north of 10k.  See the above referenced FAQ for how.</para>
      <para>To be clear, upping the file descriptors for the user who is
      running the HBase process is an operating system configuration, not an
      HBase configuration. Also, a common mistake is that administrators
      will up the file descriptors for a particular user but for whatever reason,
      HBase will be running as some one else.  HBase prints in its logs
      as the first line the ulimit its seeing.  Ensure its correct.
    <footnote>
    <para>A useful read setting config on you hadoop cluster is Aaron Kimballs'
    <link xlink:ref="http://www.cloudera.com/blog/2009/03/configuration-parameters-what-can-you-just-ignore/">Configuration Parameters: What can you just ignore?</link>
    </para>
    </footnote>
      </para>
        <section xml:id="ulimit_ubuntu">
          <title><varname>ulimit</varname> on Ubuntu</title>
        <para>
          If you are on Ubuntu you will need to make the following changes:</para>
        <para>
          In the file <filename>/etc/security/limits.conf</filename> add a line like:
          <programlisting>hadoop  -       nofile  32768</programlisting>
          Replace <varname>hadoop</varname>
          with whatever user is running Hadoop and HBase. If you have
          separate users, you will need 2 entries, one for each user.
        </para>
        <para>
          In the file <filename>/etc/pam.d/common-session</filename> add as the last line in the file:
          <programlisting>session required  pam_limits.so</programlisting>
          Otherwise the changes in <filename>/etc/security/limits.conf</filename> won't be applied.
        </para>
        <para>
          Don't forget to log out and back in again for the changes to take effect!
        </para>
          </section>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="dfs.datanode.max.xcievers">
      <title><varname>dfs.datanode.max.xcievers</varname><indexterm><primary>xcievers</primary></indexterm></title>
      <para>
      An Hadoop HDFS datanode has an upper bound on the number of files
      that it will serve at any one time.
      The upper bound parameter is called
      <varname>xcievers</varname> (yes, this is misspelled). Again, before
      doing any loading, make sure you have configured
      Hadoop's <filename>conf/hdfs-site.xml</filename>
      setting the <varname>xceivers</varname> value to at least the following:
      <programlisting>
      &lt;property&gt;
        &lt;name&gt;dfs.datanode.max.xcievers&lt;/name&gt;
        &lt;value&gt;4096&lt;/value&gt;
      &lt;/property&gt;
      </programlisting>
      </para>
      <para>Be sure to restart your HDFS after making the above
      configuration.</para>
      <para>Not having this configuration in place makes for strange looking
          failures. Eventually you'll see a complain in the datanode logs
          complaining about the xcievers exceeded, but on the run up to this
          one manifestation is complaint about missing blocks.  For example:
          <code>10/12/08 20:10:31 INFO hdfs.DFSClient: Could not obtain block blk_XXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXX_YYYYYYYY from any node: java.io.IOException: No live nodes contain current block. Will get new block locations from namenode and retry...</code>
      </para>
      </section>

<section xml:id="windows">
<title>Windows</title>
<para>
HBase has been little tested running on windows.
Running a production install of HBase on top of
windows is not recommended.
</para>
<para>
If you are running HBase on Windows, you must install
<link xlink:href="http://cygwin.com/">Cygwin</link>
to have a *nix-like environment for the shell scripts. The full details
are explained in the <link xlink:href="http://hbase.apache.org/cygwin.html">Windows Installation</link>
guide.
</para>
</section>

      </section>

      <section xml:id="standalone_dist"><title>HBase run modes: Standalone and Distributed</title>
          <para>HBase has two run modes: <link linkend="standalone">standalone</link>
              and <link linkend="distributed">distributed</link>.
              Out of the box, HBase runs in standalone mode.  To set up a
              distributed deploy, you will need to configure HBase by editing
              files in the HBase <filename>conf</filename> directory.</para>

<para>Whatever your mode, you will need to edit <code>conf/hbase-env.sh</code>
to tell HBase which <command>java</command> to use. In this file
you set HBase environment variables such as the heapsize and other options
for the <application>JVM</application>, the preferred location for log files, etc.
Set <varname>JAVA_HOME</varname> to point at the root of your
<command>java</command> install.</para>

      <section xml:id="standalone"><title>Standalone HBase</title>
        <para>This is the default mode. Standalone mode is
        what is described in the <link linkend="quickstart">quickstart</link>
        section.  In standalone mode, HBase does not use HDFS -- it uses the local
        filesystem instead -- and it runs all HBase daemons and a local zookeeper
        all up in the same JVM.  Zookeeper binds to a well known port so clients may
        talk to HBase.
      </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="distributed"><title>Distributed</title>
          <para>Distributed mode can be subdivided into distributed but all daemons run on a
          single node -- a.k.a <emphasis>pseudo-distributed</emphasis>-- and
          <emphasis>fully-distributed</emphasis> where the daemons 
          are spread across all nodes in the cluster
          <footnote><para>The pseudo-distributed vs fully-distributed nomenclature comes from Hadoop.</para></footnote>.</para>
      <para>
          Distributed modes require an instance of the
          <emphasis>Hadoop Distributed File System</emphasis> (HDFS).  See the
          Hadoop <link xlink:href="http://hadoop.apache.org/common/docs/current/api/overview-summary.html#overview_description">
          requirements and instructions</link> for how to set up a HDFS.
          Before proceeding, ensure you have an appropriate, working HDFS.
      </para>
      <para>Below we describe the different distributed setups.
      Starting, verification and exploration of your install, whether a 
      <emphasis>pseudo-distributed</emphasis> or <emphasis>fully-distributed</emphasis>
      configuration is described in a section that follows,
      <link linkend="confirm">Running and Confirming your Installation</link>.
      The same verification script applies to both deploy types.</para>

      <section xml:id="pseudo"><title>Pseudo-distributed</title>
<para>A pseudo-distributed mode is simply a distributed mode run on a single host.
Use this configuration testing and prototyping on HBase.  Do not use this configuration
for production nor for evaluating HBase performance.
</para>
<para>Once you have confirmed your HDFS setup,
edit <filename>conf/hbase-site.xml</filename>.  This is the file
into which you add local customizations and overrides for 
<link linkend="hbase_default_configurations">Default HBase Configurations</link>
and <link linkend="hdfs_client_conf">HDFS Client Configurations</link>.
Point HBase at the running Hadoop HDFS instance by setting the
<varname>hbase.rootdir</varname> property.
This property points HBase at the Hadoop filesystem instance to use.
For example, adding the properties below to your
<filename>hbase-site.xml</filename> says that HBase
should use the <filename>/hbase</filename> 
directory in the HDFS whose namenode is at port 9000 on your local machine, and that
it should run with one replica only (recommended for pseudo-distributed mode):</para>
<programlisting>
&lt;configuration&gt;
  ...
  &lt;property&gt;
    &lt;name&gt;hbase.rootdir&lt;/name&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;hdfs://localhost:9000/hbase&lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;description&gt;The directory shared by region servers.
    &lt;/description&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;property&gt;
    &lt;name&gt;dfs.replication&lt;/name&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;1&lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;description&gt;The replication count for HLog &amp; HFile storage. Should not be greater than HDFS datanode count.
    &lt;/description&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
  ...
&lt;/configuration&gt;
</programlisting>

<note>
<para>Let HBase create the <varname>hbase.rootdir</varname>
directory. If you don't, you'll get warning saying HBase
needs a migration run because the directory is missing files
expected by HBase (it'll create them if you let it).</para>
</note>

<note>
<para>Above we bind to <varname>localhost</varname>.
This means that a remote client cannot
connect.  Amend accordingly, if you want to
connect from a remote location.</para>
</note>

<para>Now skip to <link linkend="confirm">Running and Confirming your Installation</link>
for how to start and verify your pseudo-distributed install.

<footnote>
    <para>See <link xlink:href="http://hbase.apache.org/pseudo-distributed.html">Pseudo-distributed mode extras</link>
for notes on how to start extra Masters and regionservers when running
    pseudo-distributed.</para>
</footnote>
</para>

</section>

      <section xml:id="fully_dist"><title>Fully-distributed</title>

<para>For running a fully-distributed operation on more than one host, make
the following configurations.  In <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>,
add the property <varname>hbase.cluster.distributed</varname> 
and set it to <varname>true</varname> and point the HBase
<varname>hbase.rootdir</varname> at the appropriate
HDFS NameNode and location in HDFS where you would like
HBase to write data. For example, if you namenode were running
at namenode.example.org on port 9000 and you wanted to home
your HBase in HDFS at <filename>/hbase</filename>,
make the following configuration.</para>
<programlisting>
&lt;configuration&gt;
  ...
  &lt;property&gt;
    &lt;name&gt;hbase.rootdir&lt;/name&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;hdfs://namenode.example.org:9000/hbase&lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;description&gt;The directory shared by region servers.
    &lt;/description&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;property&gt;
    &lt;name&gt;hbase.cluster.distributed&lt;/name&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;true&lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;description&gt;The mode the cluster will be in. Possible values are
      false: standalone and pseudo-distributed setups with managed Zookeeper
      true: fully-distributed with unmanaged Zookeeper Quorum (see hbase-env.sh)
    &lt;/description&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
  ...
&lt;/configuration&gt;
</programlisting>

<section xml:id="regionserver"><title><filename>regionservers</filename></title>
<para>In addition, a fully-distributed mode requires that you
modify <filename>conf/regionservers</filename>.
The <filename><link linkend="regionservrers">regionservers</link></filename> file lists all hosts
that you would have running <application>HRegionServer</application>s, one host per line
(This file in HBase is like the Hadoop <filename>slaves</filename> file).  All servers
listed in this file will be started and stopped when HBase cluster start or stop is run.</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="zookeeper"><title>ZooKeeper<indexterm><primary>ZooKeeper</primary></indexterm></title>
<para>A distributed HBase depends on a running ZooKeeper cluster.
All participating nodes and clients
need to be able to access the running ZooKeeper ensemble.
HBase by default manages a ZooKeeper "cluster" for you.
It will start and stop the ZooKeeper ensemble as part of
the HBase start/stop process.  You can also manage
the ZooKeeper ensemble independent of HBase and 
just point HBase at the cluster it should use.
To toggle HBase management of ZooKeeper,
use the <varname>HBASE_MANAGES_ZK</varname> variable in
<filename>conf/hbase-env.sh</filename>.
This variable, which defaults to <varname>true</varname>, tells HBase whether to
start/stop the ZooKeeper ensemble servers as part of HBase start/stop.</para>

<para>When HBase manages the ZooKeeper ensemble, you can specify ZooKeeper configuration
using its native <filename>zoo.cfg</filename> file, or, the easier option
is to just specify ZooKeeper options directly in <filename>conf/hbase-site.xml</filename>.
A ZooKeeper configuration option can be set as a property in the HBase
<filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>
XML configuration file by prefacing the ZooKeeper option name with
<varname>hbase.zookeeper.property</varname>.
For example, the <varname>clientPort</varname> setting in ZooKeeper can be changed by
setting the <varname>hbase.zookeeper.property.clientPort</varname> property.

For all default values used by HBase, including ZooKeeper configuration,
see the section
<link linkend="hbase_default_configurations">Default HBase Configurations</link>.
Look for the <varname>hbase.zookeeper.property</varname> prefix

<footnote><para>For the full list of ZooKeeper configurations,
see ZooKeeper's <filename>zoo.cfg</filename>.
HBase does not ship with a <filename>zoo.cfg</filename> so you will need to
browse the <filename>conf</filename> directory in an appropriate ZooKeeper download.
</para>
</footnote>
</para>



<para>You must at least list the ensemble servers in <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>
using the <varname>hbase.zookeeper.quorum</varname> property.
This property defaults to a single ensemble member at
<varname>localhost</varname> which is not suitable for a
fully distributed HBase. (It binds to the local machine only and remote clients
will not be able to connect).
<note xml:id="how_many_zks">
<title>How many ZooKeepers should I run?</title>
<para>
You can run a ZooKeeper ensemble that comprises 1 node only but
in production it is recommended that you run a ZooKeeper ensemble of
3, 5 or 7 machines; the more members an ensemble has, the more
tolerant the ensemble is of host failures. Also, run an odd number of machines.
There can be no quorum if the number of members is an even number.  Give each
ZooKeeper server around 1GB of RAM, and if possible, its own dedicated disk
(A dedicated disk is the best thing you can do to ensure a performant ZooKeeper
ensemble).  For very heavily loaded clusters, run ZooKeeper servers on separate machines from
RegionServers (DataNodes and TaskTrackers).</para>
</note>
</para>


<para>For example, to have HBase manage a ZooKeeper quorum on nodes
<emphasis>rs{1,2,3,4,5}.example.com</emphasis>, bound to port 2222 (the default is 2181)
ensure <varname>HBASE_MANAGE_ZK</varname> is commented out or set to
<varname>true</varname> in <filename>conf/hbase-env.sh</filename> and
then edit <filename>conf/hbase-site.xml</filename> and set 
<varname>hbase.zookeeper.property.clientPort</varname>
and
<varname>hbase.zookeeper.quorum</varname>.  You should also
set
<varname>hbase.zookeeper.property.dataDir</varname>
to other than the default as the default has ZooKeeper persist data under
<filename>/tmp</filename> which is often cleared on system restart.
In the example below we have ZooKeeper persist to <filename>/user/local/zookeeper</filename>.
<programlisting>
  &lt;configuration&gt;
    ...
    &lt;property&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;hbase.zookeeper.property.clientPort&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;value&gt;2222&lt;/value&gt;
      &lt;description&gt;Property from ZooKeeper's config zoo.cfg.
      The port at which the clients will connect.
      &lt;/description&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;property&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;hbase.zookeeper.quorum&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;value&gt;rs1.example.com,rs2.example.com,rs3.example.com,rs4.example.com,rs5.example.com&lt;/value&gt;
      &lt;description&gt;Comma separated list of servers in the ZooKeeper Quorum.
      For example, "host1.mydomain.com,host2.mydomain.com,host3.mydomain.com".
      By default this is set to localhost for local and pseudo-distributed modes
      of operation. For a fully-distributed setup, this should be set to a full
      list of ZooKeeper quorum servers. If HBASE_MANAGES_ZK is set in hbase-env.sh
      this is the list of servers which we will start/stop ZooKeeper on.
      &lt;/description&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;property&gt;
      &lt;name&gt;hbase.zookeeper.property.dataDir&lt;/name&gt;
      &lt;value&gt;/usr/local/zookeeper&lt;/value&gt;
      &lt;description>Property from ZooKeeper's config zoo.cfg.
      The directory where the snapshot is stored.
      &lt;/description&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
    ...
  &lt;/configuration&gt;</programlisting>
</para>

<section><title>Using existing ZooKeeper ensemble</title>
<para>To point HBase at an existing ZooKeeper cluster,
one that is not managed by HBase,
set <varname>HBASE_MANAGES_ZK</varname> in 
<filename>conf/hbase-env.sh</filename> to false
<programlisting>
  ...
  # Tell HBase whether it should manage it's own instance of Zookeeper or not.
  export HBASE_MANAGES_ZK=false</programlisting>

Next set ensemble locations and client port, if non-standard,
in <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>,
or add a suitably configured <filename>zoo.cfg</filename> to HBase's <filename>CLASSPATH</filename>.
HBase will prefer the configuration found in <filename>zoo.cfg</filename>
over any settings in <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>.
</para>

<para>When HBase manages ZooKeeper, it will start/stop the ZooKeeper servers as a part
of the regular start/stop scripts. If you would like to run ZooKeeper yourself,
independent of HBase start/stop, you would do the following</para>
<programlisting>
${HBASE_HOME}/bin/hbase-daemons.sh {start,stop} zookeeper
</programlisting>

<para>Note that you can use HBase in this manner to spin up a ZooKeeper cluster,
unrelated to HBase. Just make sure to set <varname>HBASE_MANAGES_ZK</varname> to
<varname>false</varname> if you want it to stay up across HBase restarts
so that when HBase shuts down, it doesn't take ZooKeeper down with it.</para>

<para>For more information about running a distinct ZooKeeper cluster, see
the ZooKeeper <link xlink:href="http://hadoop.apache.org/zookeeper/docs/current/zookeeperStarted.html">Getting Started Guide</link>.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section xml:id="hdfs_client_conf">
<title>HDFS Client Configuration</title>
<para>Of note, if you have made <emphasis>HDFS client configuration</emphasis> on your Hadoop cluster
-- i.e. configuration you want HDFS clients to use as opposed to server-side configurations --
HBase will not see this configuration unless you do one of the following:</para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para>Add a pointer to your <varname>HADOOP_CONF_DIR</varname>
  to the <varname>HBASE_CLASSPATH</varname> environment variable
  in <filename>hbase-env.sh</filename>.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Add a copy of <filename>hdfs-site.xml</filename>
  (or <filename>hadoop-site.xml</filename>) or, better, symlinks,
  under
  <filename>${HBASE_HOME}/conf</filename>, or</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>if only a small set of HDFS client
  configurations, add them to <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>An example of such an HDFS client configuration is <varname>dfs.replication</varname>. If for example,
you want to run with a replication factor of 5, hbase will create files with the default of 3 unless
you do the above to make the configuration available to HBase.</para>
</section>
      </section>
      </section>

<section xml:id="confirm"><title>Running and Confirming Your Installation</title>
<para>Make sure HDFS is running first.
Start and stop the Hadoop HDFS daemons by running <filename>bin/start-hdfs.sh</filename>
over in the <varname>HADOOP_HOME</varname> directory.
You can ensure it started properly by testing the <command>put</command> and
<command>get</command> of files into the Hadoop filesystem.
HBase does not normally use the mapreduce daemons.  These do not need to be started.</para>

<para><emphasis>If</emphasis> you are managing your own ZooKeeper, start it
and confirm its running else, HBase will start up ZooKeeper for you as part
of its start process.</para>

<para>Start HBase with the following command:</para>
<programlisting>bin/start-hbase.sh</programlisting>
Run the above from the <varname>HBASE_HOME</varname> directory.

<para>You should now have a running HBase instance.
HBase logs can be found in the <filename>logs</filename> subdirectory. Check them
out especially if HBase had trouble starting.</para>

<para>HBase also puts up a UI listing vital attributes. By default its deployed on the Master host
at port 60010 (HBase RegionServers listen on port 60020 by default and put up an informational
http server at 60030). If the Master were running on a host named <varname>master.example.org</varname>
on the default port, to see the Master's homepage you'd point your browser at
<filename>http://master.example.org:60010</filename>.</para>

<para>Once HBase has started, see the
<link linkend="shell_exercises">Shell Exercises</link> section for how to
create tables, add data, scan your insertions, and finally disable and
drop your tables.
</para>

<para>To stop HBase after exiting the HBase shell enter
<programlisting>$ ./bin/stop-hbase.sh
stopping hbase...............</programlisting>
Shutdown can take a moment to complete.  It can take longer if your cluster
is comprised of many machines.  If you are running a distributed operation,
be sure to wait until HBase has shut down completely
before stopping the Hadoop daemons.</para>



</section>
</section>






    <section xml:id="example_config"><title>Example Configurations</title>
    <section><title>Basic Distributed HBase Install</title>
    <para>Here is an example basic configuration for a distributed ten node cluster.
    The nodes are named <varname>example0</varname>, <varname>example1</varname>, etc., through
node <varname>example9</varname>  in this example.  The HBase Master and the HDFS namenode 
are running on the node <varname>example0</varname>.  RegionServers run on nodes
<varname>example1</varname>-<varname>example9</varname>.
A 3-node ZooKeeper ensemble runs on <varname>example1</varname>,
<varname>example2</varname>, and <varname>example3</varname> on the
default ports. ZooKeeper data is persisted to the directory
<filename>/export/zookeeper</filename>.
Below we show what the main configuration files
-- <filename>hbase-site.xml</filename>, <filename>regionservers</filename>, and
<filename>hbase-env.sh</filename> -- found in the HBase
<filename>conf</filename> directory might look like.
</para>
    <section xml:id="hbase_site"><title><filename>hbase-site.xml</filename></title>
    <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="configuration.xsl"?>
<configuration>
  <property>
    <name>hbase.zookeeper.quorum</name>
    <value>example1,example2,example3</value>
    <description>The directory shared by region servers.
    </description>
  </property>
  <property>
    <name>hbase.zookeeper.property.dataDir</name>
    <value>/export/zookeeper</value>
    <description>Property from ZooKeeper's config zoo.cfg.
    The directory where the snapshot is stored.
    </description>
  </property>
  <property>
    <name>hbase.rootdir</name>
    <value>hdfs://example0:9000/hbase</value>
    <description>The directory shared by region servers.
    </description>
  </property>
  <property>
    <name>hbase.cluster.distributed</name>
    <value>true</value>
    <description>The mode the cluster will be in. Possible values are
      false: standalone and pseudo-distributed setups with managed Zookeeper
      true: fully-distributed with unmanaged Zookeeper Quorum (see hbase-env.sh)
    </description>
  </property>
</configuration>
]]>
    </programlisting>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="regionservers"><title><filename>regionservers</filename></title>
    <para>In this file you list the nodes that will run regionservers.  In
    our case we run regionservers on all but the head node
    <varname>example1</varname> which is
    carrying the HBase Master and the HDFS namenode</para>
    <programlisting>
    example1
    example3
    example4
    example5
    example6
    example7
    example8
    example9
    </programlisting>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="hbase_env"><title><filename>hbase-env.sh</filename></title>
    <para>Below we use a <command>diff</command> to show the differences from 
    default in the <filename>hbase-env.sh</filename> file. Here we are setting
the HBase heap to be 4G instead of the default 1G.
    </para>
    <programlisting>
    <![CDATA[
$ git diff hbase-env.sh
diff --git a/conf/hbase-env.sh b/conf/hbase-env.sh
index e70ebc6..96f8c27 100644
--- a/conf/hbase-env.sh
+++ b/conf/hbase-env.sh
@@ -31,7 +31,7 @@ export JAVA_HOME=/usr/lib//jvm/java-6-sun/
 # export HBASE_CLASSPATH=
 
 # The maximum amount of heap to use, in MB. Default is 1000.
-# export HBASE_HEAPSIZE=1000
+export HBASE_HEAPSIZE=4096
 
 # Extra Java runtime options.
 # Below are what we set by default.  May only work with SUN JVM.
]]>
    </programlisting>

    <para>Use <command>rsync</command> to copy the content of
    the <filename>conf</filename> directory to
    all nodes of the cluster.
    </para>
    </section>

    </section>
    
    </section>
    </section>

  </chapter>
