<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="ops_mgt"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>HBase Operational Management</title>
  This chapter will cover operational tools and practices required of a running HBase cluster.
  The subject of operations is related to the topics of <xref linkend="trouble" />, <xref linkend="performance"/>,
  and <xref linkend="configuration" /> but is a distinct topic in itself.  
  
  <section xml:id="tools">
    <title >HBase Tools and Utilities</title>

    <para>Here we list HBase tools for administration, analysis, fixup, and
    debugging.</para>
    <section xml:id="hbck">
        <title>HBase <application>hbck</application></title>
        <subtitle>An <emphasis>fsck</emphasis> for your HBase install</subtitle>
        <para>To run <application>hbck</application> against your HBase cluster run
        <programlisting>$ ./bin/hbase hbck</programlisting>
        At the end of the commands output it prints <emphasis>OK</emphasis>
        or <emphasis>INCONSISTENCY</emphasis>. If your cluster reports
        inconsistencies, pass <command>-details</command> to see more detail emitted.
        If inconsistencies, run <command>hbck</command> a few times because the
        inconsistency may be transient (e.g. cluster is starting up or a region is
        splitting).
        Passing <command>-fix</command> may correct the inconsistency (This latter
        is an experimental feature).
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="hfile_tool2"><title>HFile Tool</title>
        <para>See <xref linkend="hfile_tool" />.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="wal_tools">
      <title>WAL Tools</title>

      <section xml:id="hlog_tool">
        <title><classname>HLog</classname> tool</title>

        <para>The main method on <classname>HLog</classname> offers manual
        split and dump facilities. Pass it WALs or the product of a split, the
        content of the <filename>recovered.edits</filename>. directory.</para>

        <para>You can get a textual dump of a WAL file content by doing the
        following:<programlisting> <code>$ ./bin/hbase org.apache.hadoop.hbase.regionserver.wal.HLog --dump hdfs://example.org:8020/hbase/.logs/example.org,60020,1283516293161/10.10.21.10%3A60020.1283973724012</code> </programlisting>The
        return code will be non-zero if issues with the file so you can test
        wholesomeness of file by redirecting <varname>STDOUT</varname> to
        <code>/dev/null</code> and testing the program return.</para>

        <para>Similarily you can force a split of a log file directory by
        doing:<programlisting> $ ./<code>bin/hbase org.apache.hadoop.hbase.regionserver.wal.HLog --split hdfs://example.org:8020/hbase/.logs/example.org,60020,1283516293161/</code></programlisting></para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="compression.tool"><title>Compression Tool</title>
        <para>See <xref linkend="compression.tool" />.</para>
    </section>
        <section xml:id="copytable">
        <title>CopyTable</title>
      <para>
            CopyTable is a utility that can copy part or of all of a table, either to the same cluster or another cluster. The usage is as follows:
<programlisting>$ bin/hbase org.apache.hadoop.hbase.mapreduce.CopyTable [--rs.class=CLASS] [--rs.impl=IMPL] [--starttime=X] [--endtime=Y] [--new.name=NEW] [--peer.adr=ADR] tablename
</programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>
        Options:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><varname>rs.class</varname> hbase.regionserver.class of the peer cluster.  Specify if different from current cluster.</listitem>
          <listitem><varname>rs.impl</varname>  hbase.regionserver.impl of the peer cluster. </listitem>
          <listitem><varname>starttime</varname>  Beginning of the time range.  Without endtime means starttime to forever.</listitem>
          <listitem><varname>endtime</varname>  End of the time range.  Without endtime means starttime to forever.</listitem>
          <listitem><varname>new.name</varname>  New table's name.</listitem>
          <listitem><varname>peer.adr</varname>  Address of the peer cluster given in the format hbase.zookeeper.quorum:hbase.zookeeper.client.port:zookeeper.znode.parent</listitem>
          <listitem><varname>families</varname>  Comma-separated list of ColumnFamilies to copy.</listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
         Args:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>tablename  Name of table to copy.</listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>Example of copying 'TestTable' to a cluster that uses replication for a 1 hour window:
<programlisting>$ bin/hbase org.apache.hadoop.hbase.mapreduce.CopyTable
--rs.class=org.apache.hadoop.hbase.ipc.ReplicationRegionInterface
--rs.impl=org.apache.hadoop.hbase.regionserver.replication.ReplicationRegionServer
--starttime=1265875194289 --endtime=1265878794289
--peer.adr=server1,server2,server3:2181:/hbase TestTable</programlisting>
        </para>
    </section>       
    </section>  <!--  tools -->
    
    <section xml:id="node.management"><title>Node Management</title>
     <section xml:id="decommission"><title>Node Decommission</title>
        <para>You can stop an individual RegionServer by running the following
            script in the HBase directory on the particular  node:
            <programlisting>$ ./bin/hbase-daemon.sh stop regionserver</programlisting>
            The RegionServer will first close all regions and then shut itself down.
            On shutdown, the RegionServer's ephemeral node in ZooKeeper will expire.
            The master will notice the RegionServer gone and will treat it as
            a 'crashed' server; it will reassign the nodes the RegionServer was carrying.
            <note><title>Disable the Load Balancer before Decommissioning a node</title>
             <para>If the load balancer runs while a node is shutting down, then
                 there could be contention between the Load Balancer and the
                 Master's recovery of the just decommissioned RegionServer.
                 Avoid any problems by disabling the balancer first.
                 See <xref linkend="lb" /> below.
             </para>
            </note>
        </para>
        <para>
        A downside to the above stop of a RegionServer is that regions could be offline for
        a good period of time.  Regions are closed in order.  If many regions on the server, the
        first region to close may not be back online until all regions close and after the master
        notices the RegionServer's znode gone.  In HBase 0.90.2, we added facility for having
        a node gradually shed its load and then shutdown itself down.  HBase 0.90.2 added the
            <filename>graceful_stop.sh</filename> script.  Here is its usage:
            <programlisting>$ ./bin/graceful_stop.sh 
Usage: graceful_stop.sh [--config &amp;conf-dir>] [--restart] [--reload] [--thrift] [--rest] &amp;hostname>
 thrift      If we should stop/start thrift before/after the hbase stop/start
 rest        If we should stop/start rest before/after the hbase stop/start
 restart     If we should restart after graceful stop
 reload      Move offloaded regions back on to the stopped server
 debug       Move offloaded regions back on to the stopped server
 hostname    Hostname of server we are to stop</programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>
            To decommission a loaded RegionServer, run the following:
            <programlisting>$ ./bin/graceful_stop.sh HOSTNAME</programlisting>
            where <varname>HOSTNAME</varname> is the host carrying the RegionServer
            you would decommission.  
            <note><title>On <varname>HOSTNAME</varname></title>
                <para>The <varname>HOSTNAME</varname> passed to <filename>graceful_stop.sh</filename>
            must match the hostname that hbase is using to identify RegionServers.
            Check the list of RegionServers in the master UI for how HBase is
            referring to servers. Its usually hostname but can also be FQDN.
            Whatever HBase is using, this is what you should pass the
            <filename>graceful_stop.sh</filename> decommission
            script.  If you pass IPs, the script is not yet smart enough to make
            a hostname (or FQDN) of it and so it will fail when it checks if server is
            currently running; the graceful unloading of regions will not run.
            </para>
        </note> The <filename>graceful_stop.sh</filename> script will move the regions off the
            decommissioned RegionServer one at a time to minimize region churn.
            It will verify the region deployed in the new location before it
            will moves the next region and so on until the decommissioned server
            is carrying zero regions.  At this point, the <filename>graceful_stop.sh</filename>
            tells the RegionServer <command>stop</command>.  The master will at this point notice the
            RegionServer gone but all regions will have already been redeployed
            and because the RegionServer went down cleanly, there will be no
            WAL logs to split.
            <note xml:id="lb"><title>Load Balancer</title>
            <para> 
                It is assumed that the Region Load Balancer is disabled while the
                <command>graceful_stop</command> script runs (otherwise the balancer
                and the decommission script will end up fighting over region deployments).
                Use the shell to disable the balancer:
                <programlisting>hbase(main):001:0> balance_switch false
true
0 row(s) in 0.3590 seconds</programlisting>
This turns the balancer OFF.  To reenable, do:
                <programlisting>hbase(main):001:0> balance_switch true
false
0 row(s) in 0.3590 seconds</programlisting>
            </para> 
        </note>
        </para>
        </section>  
        <section xml:id="rolling">
            <title>Rolling Restart</title>
        <para>
            You can also ask this script to restart a RegionServer after the shutdown
            AND move its old regions back into place.  The latter you might do to
            retain data locality.  A primitive rolling restart might be effected by
            running something like the following:
            <programlisting>$ for i in `cat conf/regionservers|sort`; do ./bin/graceful_stop.sh --restart --reload --debug $i; done &amp;> /tmp/log.txt &amp;
            </programlisting>
            Tail the output of <filename>/tmp/log.txt</filename> to follow the scripts
            progress. The above does RegionServers only.  Be sure to disable the
            load balancer before doing the above.  You'd need to do the master
            update separately.  Do it before you run the above script.
            Here is a pseudo-script for how you might craft a rolling restart script:
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem><para>Untar your release, make sure of its configuration and
                        then rsync it across the cluster. If this is 0.90.2, patch it
                        with HBASE-3744 and HBASE-3756.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Run hbck to ensure the cluster consistent
                        <programlisting>$ ./bin/hbase hbck</programlisting>
                    Effect repairs if inconsistent.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Restart the Master: <programlisting>$ ./bin/hbase-daemon.sh stop master; ./bin/hbase-daemon.sh start master</programlisting>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                       Disable the region balancer:<programlisting>$ echo "balance_switch false" | ./bin/hbase shell</programlisting>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                     <para>Run the <filename>graceful_stop.sh</filename> script per RegionServer.  For example:
            <programlisting>$ for i in `cat conf/regionservers|sort`; do ./bin/graceful_stop.sh --restart --reload --debug $i; done &amp;> /tmp/log.txt &amp;
            </programlisting>
                     If you are running thrift or rest servers on the RegionServer, pass --thrift or --rest options (See usage
                     for <filename>graceful_stop.sh</filename> script).
                 </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Restart the Master again.  This will clear out dead servers list and reenable the balancer.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Run hbck to ensure the cluster is consistent.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
    </section>  <!--  node mgt -->

  <section xml:id="ops.monitoring">
    <title >HBase Monitoring</title>
    <para>TODO
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ops.backup">
    <title >HBase Backup</title>
    <para>See <link xlink:href="http://blog.sematext.com/2011/03/11/hbase-backup-options/">HBase Backup Options</link> over on the Sematext Blog.
    </para>
  </section>

</chapter>
